<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe narration of some church courses held in opinion and practise in the churches lately erected in New England. Collected out of sundry of their own printed papers and manuscripts with other good intelligences. Together with some short hints (given by the way) of their correspondence with the like tenents and practises of the separatists churches. And some short animadversions upon some principall passages for the benefit of the vulgar reader. Presented to publike view for the good of the church of God by W. R.</title>
            <author>Rathband, William, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E36_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21802</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871508</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E36[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe narration of some church courses held in opinion and practise in the churches lately erected in New England. Collected out of sundry of their own printed papers and manuscripts with other good intelligences. Together with some short hints (given by the way) of their correspondence with the like tenents and practises of the separatists churches. And some short animadversions upon some principall passages for the benefit of the vulgar reader. Presented to publike view for the good of the church of God by W. R.</title>
                  <author>Rathband, William, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M. for Edward Brewster at the Signe of the Bible on Fleet-bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W. R. is William Rathband.  Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: The 4 in the imprint date is crossed out and altered to 1643; "March 9th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New England --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE NARRATION OF SOME Church Courſes Held in Opinion and Practiſe in the Churches lately erected in <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected out of ſundry of their own printed Papers and Manuſcripts with other good Intelligences.</p>
            <p>Together with ſome ſhort hints (given by the way) of their correſpondence with the like tenents and practiſes of the Separatiſts Churches.</p>
            <p>And ſome ſhort Animadverſions upon ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall paſſages for the benefit of the vulgar Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preſented to publike view for the good of the Church of God by</hi> W. R.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewster</hi> at the Signe of the Bible on Fleet-bridge. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155017:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155017:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ive me leave before I preſent thee with the Narration following to Apologize ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for my ſelf. I have not fallen upon this taske for want of other work; nor out of any itching much leſse ambitious deſire to appeare in print, which as I never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, ſo much leſse now, when it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come no ſingular praiſe. For <hi>Scribimus omnes, indocti, doctique;</hi> nor out of any malignancie of ſpirit againſt the men (whoſe Church wayes I here relate) whom ſo farre as I know them, I profeſſe (God and my Conſcience bearing me witneſſe) highly to love and honour in the Lord. But the firſt occaſion of my thoughts in this kind was, that a ſolemne agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being a good while ſince made between the brethren of the independent way (then and ſtill reſiding in London) and thoſe of the oppoſite judgement, wherein (amongst other things on both ſides agreed upon) thoſe brethren promiſed then ſhortly to put forth a narrative of their doctrine and practiſe in Church courſes, that ſo it might appear where the differences lay: which Narrative being once publiſhed (the materials whereof they then profeſſed to be all ready) they alſo promiſed to joyne with the rest in preaching againſt the <hi>Browniſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and other Sectaries. But the ſaid brethren (though ſundry times called upon to put forth their Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive according to promiſe) have yet not onely delayed, but at
<pb facs="tcp:155017:3"/>length altogether denied to doe the ſame: upon which deniall I began to entertaine ſome thoughts of making a Narrative my ſelfe; and began ſo to doe, but through many diſcouragements I laid it by againe; till of late ſome of the ſaid brethren that had formerly promiſed the Narrative, publiſhed a Narration apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logeticall, which ſeemed in title to me a performance of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ingagement; but when I had read it, I found it nothing leſse, as being neither full nor cleare as a Narration ought to be. But touching that I will ſay no more, becauſe others better able have, and I hope will deale throughly with it: Onely I let the Reader know that upon this occaſion I reſumed my former pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, conſidering now the neceſsitie of ſuch a courſe, in regard that not onely themſelves continued in that way, but alſo others both Miniſters and people out of ignorance or inconſideration were daily drawn aſide thereto, new Churches were erected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their module, our Churches and Ministerie, and Gods Ordinances in them began to be neglected, ſlighted, deſerted, yea, contumeliouſly and ſcornfully reproached as Antichristian, Babyloniſh, falſe and null, that many were distracted and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what to hold and doe, and to which ſide to cleave, ſome thought better of their wayes, and others worſe, then they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and both ſorts for want of right information what they were. That the full relation of their wayes, if it did not turne men quite off from them, yet, at least, might ſo far prevaile as to make men pauſe awhile, and enquire further into them before they were too far ingaged; eſpecially might give occaſion of a more full agitation of all theſe differences in this venerable Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines now met for conſultation about matters of this nature. That all the printed bookes which I had ſeen did not together make out a full ſtory, and what was in them here and there diſperſed could not be ſo ſatisfactorie as to ſee all things together in a ſhort <hi>Synopſis</hi> with one view. That my ſelfe by divine providence had ſundry intelligences lay by me,
<pb facs="tcp:155017:3"/>which joyned to what was already printed might either make the ſtorie compleat, or elſe might occaſion and ſpurre on ſome other (perhaps of themſelves) to publiſh a better. And laſtly, that ſome of that way contrary to their former promiſes and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and laying by not onely the due regard we thinke they ſhould have had of their brethren of the contrary judgement, but alſo of the publike peace and common cauſe of Reformation, (which by ſuch distractions is retarded) have impetuouſly both in Pulpit and Preſſe (beſides what they have done in private) laboured to promote theſe their popular Church wayes, as the only wayes of God, and to make all men, they could, to diſ-relliſh and abominate that which (for distinction ſake) we call <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Government. Theſe and other like things (after much pondering in my ſpirit) at laſt caſt the ballance, and cauſed me to reſolve to purſue my firſt intention in this way, as here you ſee.</p>
            <p>Now lest I be miſtaken, I deſire the Reader to underſtand and heare in mind that I intend not in this Relation to ſet down all things which they hold or practiſe in Diſcipline or Church-Government, but ſuch things onely or for the most part, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there lies ſome difference betweene them and us, or other the beſt Reformed Churches. Neither doe I intend to wrap up all and every one of the <hi>Elders</hi> (much leſſe members) of the <hi>New England</hi> Churches in the ſame imputations: Foraſmuch as it is moſt certain, that though in practiſe they act generally all alike, yet in their opinion of things practiſed, much more in the grounds and reaſons thereof, ſome of them doe not onely differ from the reſt, but have ſtiffely oppoſed the reſt therein, which I write to preſerve the just repute of ſome eminent perſons there, from ſuch cenſures and hard opinions as others of them, perhaps, may ſeeme to merit, and incurre.</p>
            <p>Lastly, becauſe every common Reader cannot ſo eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and diſtinguiſh of all things here preſented to him, therfore I crave leave ere I part to give him ſome few directions: Firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:155017:4"/>he muſt take notice that the whole Narration is divided into ſeverall Chapters, and each Chapter into ſeverall Articles, printed in a Larger Character. <hi>2</hi> At the end of thoſe ſeverall Articles are ſet down the proofs thereof collected out of their printed Papers, and other Manuſcripts of their own either Treatiſes or Letters written from one friend in <hi>New England</hi> to another here, the Originals or Copies whereof, at leaſt, I have by me, to produce, if need ſhall ſo require. <hi>3.</hi> After the ſaid proofs of the ſeverall Articles, there uſually follow by themſelves ſome ſhort quotations of ſome one or more writers of the <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> which being conſulted with, it will appeare, that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practiſes of theſe our brethren in Church Courſes mentioned in the preceding Articles doe very much agree with them. A compleat paralell, I confeſse, in all things here is not: partly through want of ſome <hi>Browniſts</hi> Bookes, partly want of leaſure to view over thoſe I had, partly alſo, I beleeve, for want of full agreement between them. For though in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan e of things there be too great an accord, yet in ſome forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities or other acceſsories there may be differences; in ſome things ſome of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> being more rigid then theſe our brethren are, as in other things theſe ſeeme more ſtrict then any of them for ought that by their writings doth appeare. <hi>4.</hi> Over aginst many of the ſeverall Articles, and ſometimes alſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the ſame there are ſuggested ſome ſhort Animadverſions, not in way of a ſet confutation, (that taske is now in better hands) but ſometimes by way of <hi>quaere,</hi> or doubt, ſometimes pointing (as it were with the finger) to ſome ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to their own tenents or practiſes, or ſome apparant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie to the letter of <hi>Scripture,</hi> or light of common ſenſe, added only of purpoſe to admoniſh the vulgar and injudicious <hi>Reader,</hi> leſt by reading things ſo plauſibly put forth (as ſome of them are) he ſhould be inſnared at unawares. <hi>5.</hi> Sometimes proofs are more ſparingly affixed to the Article, or perhaps
<pb facs="tcp:155017:4"/>none at all, becauſe the things aſſerted in the Article are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant by the proofs of other Articles fore-going, or by the generall tenour of the whole diſcourſe, out of which the <hi>Reader</hi> himſelf may eaſily (if he be willing) make out a more full proofe. <hi>6.</hi> Nor is it alwayes to be expected, that the proofes under every Article ſhould reach every <hi>Punctilio</hi> in that Article, ſo the ſubſtance be proved, the reſt will neceſſarily follow of their own accord. <hi>7.</hi> Nor that every proofe ſhould make good every part of the Article; I hope it may ſuffice if all the proofes together will doe it amongst them. <hi>8.</hi> Laſtly, the <hi>Reader</hi> must know that when he finds quoted, <hi>Anſ. to 32. q.</hi> and <hi>Anſ. to 9. Poſ.</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov.</hi> he is to look for theſe in the booke lately publiſhed by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> H. Peters. Cott. cat.</hi> I call that Treatiſe printed under <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottons</hi> name of Church conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by way of queſtion and anſwer. There are alſo cited two other printed Letters under the ſame name. When thou meeteſt with <hi>Apol.</hi> that is, <hi>The Apologie of the Churches in New England for Church Covenant,</hi> which I have by me in a Manuſcript. Moſt of the other quotations are of Letters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween friend and friend: when you have <hi>Rob. Apol.</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Allegation of the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and is a distinct book from the former Apology. The reſt are more eaſie. Now the bleſsing of Heaven goe with this poore Pamphlet, that it may contribute ſome mite to the promoting of the publike good, whereunto it is devoted. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:155017:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155017:5"/>
            <head>A briefe NARRATION Of ſome Church Courſes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally held in opinion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe by the Churches lately erected in <hi>New England.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Concerning a Plat-forme of Church-Government and Diſcipline in generall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is to be obſerved and remembred all along, that all the Churches in <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> eſpecially within Maſſachuſets bay, at <hi>New</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">The Church at <hi>N. Plimmouth</hi> was (as I am informed) one of the firſt Churches that was ſetled there; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been a part of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robinſons</hi> Church in <hi>Holland</hi> (that famous Browniſt) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they brought with them their Church opinions and practiſes into <hi>N. E.</hi> and which they there ſtill hold and practiſe without any alteration, ſo farre as ever I could learne. If therefore they and the reſt of the Churches be all of the ſame way, <hi>Quere</hi> whether they be not all of the Separatiſts way, at leaſt, in practiſe: the rather if that be true which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>W.</hi> an eminent man of the Church at <hi>Plimmouth</hi> told <hi>W. R.</hi> That the reſt of the Churches in <hi>New Eng.</hi> came at firſt to them at <hi>Plimmouth</hi> to crave their direction in Church courſes, and made them their pattern. Alſo I find that Church much commended by <hi>I. C.</hi> in his printed letter to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>W.</hi> p 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Plimmouth, Quillipiacke,</hi> and about the river of <hi>Connectecute</hi> are of one and the ſame way in Church Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Government and Diſcipline, without any materiall dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, ſo that what may be truly ſaid of any one of them, may be beleeved of them all. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. q. p. 82. <hi>J. C.</hi> to <hi>A. H. J. W.</hi> in anſw. to 10. <hi>Q. J. D.</hi> to <hi>L. H.</hi> So all affirme <hi>uno ore.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155017:6"/>
               <p n="2">2. Yet have they no ſet Plat-forme ſolemnly agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt them. But onely they have<note n="b" place="margin">How ſhould ſuch an exact uniformity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches happen without any expreſſe agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Not by miraculous providence, nor immediate inſpiration, I ſuppoſe. If by the cleare evidence of the way reveiled in the Scriptures, and ſhining forth to them, then its a wonder that no other Churches in the world ſhould ſee that light which yet all the Churches in <hi>N. E.</hi> and all their members do ſo clearly ſee, as to practiſe uniformlie without difference, much more that all other Churches ſhould oppoſe it. If by imitation and preſident, one following another, Then <hi>quaere,</hi> whether this be not a more rationall courſe, and likely to be leſſe erroneous, that the Churches ſhould joyntly conſider of, agree upon, and in writing ſet down a ſet Plat-forme according to Reaſon and Scripture-Rule, to be obſerved amongſt them, rather then to tye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo to preſident, which if cloſely followed is ſlaviſh, and worſe, if looſly, will ſoon breed differences, if not diviſions. And it is not unknowne that ſome ſuch have beene already amongſt them.</note> all acted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into one and the ſame way. <hi>J. W.</hi> in anſw. to 10. <hi>Q. V. S.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The reaſon why they have no ſet Plat-forme agreed upon is rendred by ſome of them, to be becauſe ſuch an one is unneceſſary; yea,<note n="c" place="margin">Is not a Pattern vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually a Plat-forme, if therefore this be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how can that be juſtified? Again, let the Reader obſerve that the Anſwerers (in Anſ. to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 63, 64.) ſpeake of ſuch a Plat-forme of Doctrine and Diſcipline, and ſo impoſed [as a binding rule of Faith and practiſe, ſo that all men muſt beleeve and walke according to that Plat-forme without adding, altering, or omitting] but of a Plat-forme ſo impoſed, the queſtion whereto they anſwer was not put, nor reaſonably could be underſtood; Nor is there any ſuch amongſt the Proteſtant Churches, who acknowledge all their plat-formes imperfect, intend to binde themſelves thereto no longer, nor further then they ſhall ſee them warranted by Gods word, and therefore alwayes leave themſelves a libertie to adde to, alter, or repeale any thing therein, as God ſhall give them more light: that clauſe therefore ſo inſerted, ſerves for no other uſe but to put a greater <hi>odium</hi> upon the queſtion, and a fairer gloſſe upon the anſwere then either of them deſerved. Beſides if a tyrannicall and imperious impoſition of a Plat-forme be ſo evill in their eyes, (as alſo it is in ours) then why do they ſo rigorouſly preſſe others (that come amongſt them) to ſuch a perfect conformitie to their preſident, In that they permit no man whatſoever to be a member in any of their Churches, or partake with them in any Church-fellowſhip, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he exactly enter in their way of entring, and walke in their order. Nor will owne others as Siſter-Churches that differ from them (though but in ſome things) in Church Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline? All which to be ſo will after appeare: Is not this really a more rigid impoſition of their pattern, then any Church ever uſed in urging of their Plat-forme? and that the more inſufferable, becauſe in other Churches the rule is agreed upon, and (for the time at leaſt) fixed, and publikely held forth in writing, ſo that a man may underſtand before-hand what he binds himſelfe unto, and what he may looke for afterwards. Whereas our brethrens courſe is held forth obſcurely in practiſe only, and how long that practiſe will continue uniforme in all their Churches, yea, or in any one of them, he can have no aſſurance, nor how often or how farre they may change he cannot tell; ſo that he makes but a blinde bargaine at the beſt. <hi>Obj.</hi> There is a Plat-forme ſent over lately called, <hi>The way of the Churches in N. E. Anſw.</hi> True, but 1. that is but a meere relation of what hitherto they have practiſed without any obligation (by vertue of any agreement) to the ſame courſes hereafter. 2. Its compiled by one particular man, not conſented to by the reſt, as from thence we are informed, and therefore warned by ſome of themſelves, ſo to look at it, and no otherwiſe.</note> inconvenient, if not utterly unlawfull, at leaſt ſo as to be impoſed on the Churches; as <hi>J. W.</hi> in anſ. to 10. <hi>Q.</hi> implieth, where he ſaith, We all walke in the ſame way, but not by any publike and ſolemne agreement, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing to any what to doe. See the <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 63. 64. at large.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155017:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the true viſible Church of Christ in generall, and the bounds thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey currantly hold that there is no viſible Church of Chriſt now in the dayes of the Goſpell, but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, which may conſiſt of a very ſmall number, as<note n="d" place="margin">Though it were granted that-there is now no viſible church indued with power of Govern. and in which Church Ordinances may bee adminiſtred (for of ſuch onely vve here ſpeake) but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, yet it may be a <hi>Quare,</hi> 1. Whether ſo few as 7.8. or 9. may make up ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat organicall body fitted for exerciſe of Church power. For ſuppoſe one of the 7. or 8. members of this Church offend his brother, the brother offended admoniſheth him, he denies it, one or two more of them muſt be called in to witneſſe it, yet he relents not, one or two more yet muſt be joyned to the firſt, the party offended, to joyn in the ſecond admonition, yet ſtill he is obſtinate, novv the matter ſhould be brought to the Church, who muſt be another company from the former, (for they are all plaintiffes or witneſſes, and therefore cannot be judges in the cauſe) Alſo that Church muſt be in reaſon a greater body, and of higher authoritie then the former, but in this ſmall number of 7. or 8. where will ſuch a Church be found? Therefore in a Church conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting but of 7. 8. or 9. no cenſure can paſſe, much leſſe any other Church act be ſped. Againe, how can ſo few either imploy, or ordinarily maintaine officers of ſo many ſorts as themſelves hold neceſſaried in every Church? and if they cannot have officers, how ſhould they have Church Ordinances regularly? 2. It may be a <hi>quaere</hi> whether this particular Church may lawfully be no more in number then one only Congregation, ſince the Apoſtles Churches (moſt at leaſt if not all) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of ſo many thouſands as poſſibly could not meet all conveniently together in the ſame place, and at the ſame times for all Gods publike Worſhip to Edification. For which ſee more in Maſter <hi>Rutherfords</hi> and Maſter <hi>Bals</hi> late Treatiſes. Neither doe we ever read of any more Churches in one place or citie, and the neighbourhood, but one, which (though multiplyed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much) yet was never ſubdivided into more Churches then one, yet might be and were ſo many as poſſibly could not meet together in one congregation for Worſhip, unleſſe both the place were very ſpacious (which uſually they then had not) &amp; withall the Miniſter that did offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate had both a bodie of braſſe, and voice like a Trumpet. Men of ordinary ſtrength not being able to ſpeake audibly to above two or three thouſand at the moſt, and moſt men not to one. Much leſſe can half ſo many communicate at the Lords Table at once. Beſides, how will ever any competent number in countrey villages, and places leſſe populous, be ever joyned together into one Church, eſpecially if we be ſo curious in choice of our members as our <hi>N. E.</hi> brethren are? Surely we muſt either take ſuch inconſiderable numbers as they doe, and as can neither imploy nor maintaine Church-officers (which would bring with it unſufferable inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) or elſe they muſt be fetched from places ſo far diſtant, as muſt force them either to travell far from their ſeverall abodes to the ſame meeting place for worſhip Winter and Summer, or elſe many of them to be without all Church-Ordinances, or to enjoy them rarely: the former of which is oppreſſive to their bodies, the later injurious to their ſouls, neither of them ſeemes ſutable to the goodneſſe and wiſedome of God, who (as 'tis ſaid of the Sabbath) hath made Church-ordinances for man, not man for Church-ordinances. But I intend no diſpute, I only propound my doubts.</note> 7.8. or 9. perſons, but may not exceed the number of ſo many as conveniently may and ordinarily doe meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one Congregation, in the ſame place, and at the ſame times, for the ſolemne worſhip of God to their mutuall edification. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 9. 10. 43. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R. H. W.</hi> to Maſter <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See Johnſ. plea, p.</hi> 250. <hi>Rob. Apol. p.</hi> 12. <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 107. 108. 111.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:155017:7"/>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore they deny all<note n="e" place="margin">True in ſuch ſence as the Jewiſh church was: For they had a place of Nationall meeting, the Temple; a nationall worſhip in the ſacrifices, nationall officers the Prieſts; and therefore at certaine times all the nation (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatively in the males) came up to that place and worſhip. But (though not in that) yet in ſome other ſenſe may be admitted both a Nationall Church and Provinciall, yea, and Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan too; as a Domeſticall Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Philem.</hi> 2. As all the ſcattered Jewiſh Churches are called one flock, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2. and all the Gentiliſh Chriſtian Churches preſent were called one little Siſter, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. And the Jewiſh Chriſtian Churches yet to come are called one Bride, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.7. And the Scriptures oft ſpeake of many Churches, or all, as one in the ſingular number, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. by reaſon of ſome bonds by which they are united togethert. And our brethren themſelves do ſometimes acknowledge an univerſall viſible Church (though uſually they deny it) as <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 16. 21. 37. 40. yea, and officers too of that Catholique Church, <hi>viz.</hi> Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, which therefore (whiles they remained) baptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into that Church, whereſoever they met with them without any reſpect to a congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church, as themſelves acknowledge.</note> Nationall and Provinciall Churches, much more an univerſall viſible Church in any ſenſe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62. 63. 66. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 7. 23. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. justif. p.</hi> 217.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Alſo they deny all<note n="f" place="margin">Yet ſometimes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are forced to uſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners or Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers to repreſent the whole body ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. As at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of any new church, as after fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. So in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate examinations of members to be admitted. As after too. Eſpecially in their late Synod at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>N. E.</hi> And alwayes that part of the Church which is preſent includes others that are abſent by repreſentation, and the males the women.</note> repreſentative Churches, whether the officers of one particular Congregation repreſenting that Church in the judicature within it ſelfe, or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155017:7"/>of ſeverall Churches meeting together in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Presbyterie or Synod repreſenting all thoſe Churches by whom they are ſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> 162.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This particular viſible Church they define to this effect, It is a myſticall body whereof Chriſt is the head, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are Saints, called out of the world, and united together into<note n="g" place="margin">Here is intimated the number how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they may not be, <hi>viz.</hi> not above one Congregation, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſaid of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how few: But me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks regard ſhould have been had of the one as well as the other, left a gap be opened to cut and mangle the Churches of God into ſuch ſmall ſhreds, as will not onely occaſion num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe differences amongſt themſelves, but alſo render them odious and contemptible to all men. Which we ſee frequently fals out amongſt the <hi>Browniſts</hi> that follow the ſame church-courſes as theſe our brethren do. 2. Neither is here any mention of the church-officers as any part of this definition. But how can this be a compleat organicall body, fitted for exerciſe of all functions of the body, where there are not ſome to be tongues and eyes as well as others to be hands and feet thereto: <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome to rule, as well as others to be ruled?</note> one Congregation by an holy Covenant to worſhip the Lord and edifie one another in all his holy ordinances, <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſw.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the matter of a true viſible Church, what is required thereunto, and how the ſame may be known.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THe matter of a true viſible Church, is either infants, or perſons of age and underſtanding.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In perſons of age they require firſt that they be all reall <note n="h" place="margin">All the members of the viſible Church ſhould be Saints, holy, &amp;c. but there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and federall holineſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. and I reall internall holineſſe. That is abſolutely neceſſary to Church eſtate, this not, what ſhall become of our intants elſe? we ſhall exclude them as <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> doe, unleſſe we fly to that ſhift which <hi>Rob.</hi> (<hi>juſt if. p</hi> 309.) doth, that all infants within the Church are truly converted, and ſo as fit materials for a Church as the beſt elder people are. 2. Reall and internall holineſſe is doubtleſſe required of all Church-members, <hi>viz. in foro. interno,</hi> and unto acceptation with God, but not <hi>in foro externo,</hi> and unto admiſſion into the Church. 3. There is a double [ought to be Saints] or obligation to reall holineſſe: one morall, <hi>vi praecepti,</hi> becauſe God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all his people to be holy, as he is holy, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. another Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall, as abſolutely neceſſary to the meere being of the Church, and without which it were a falſe Church, no Church. In the former ſenſe all are bound to be holy, not in this latter. <hi>R.</hi> For if it were ſo eſſentiall, then either that all ſhould be ſo holy, or that ſome of them onely: Not that all, for then that would overthrow the truth not only of all the Churches in the world beſides, but alſo of their own too; into which not only their reaſon, but alſo their experience hath taught them that both hypocrites and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks may wind in themſelves. Nor that ſome of them onely: For there is no more reaſon for ſome to be bound, to be holy, then for all. Beſides at the execting of ſome Church: Suppoſe the firſt 7. or 8. that combine in Church-covenant ſhould all prove hypocrites (as tis not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) but not as yet diſcovered, whether is this a true viſible Church or no? And if another (though a true beleever) joyne himſelfe to them, is he a member of a true viſible Church or no? How ſhall he know his ſtanding in that Church to be lawfull? or how can he in faith continue in their fellowſhip, partake with them in ordinances, and ſubmit to their cenſures, or joyn with them in cenſuring of others? ſeeing (by this rule) they being none of them true Saints but all hypocrites, that their Church wanted true matter, and ſo was uncapable of the true forme of a Church, and therefore proves a falſe church, and all their church acts (and his with them) are ſo many nullities, uſurpations, prevarications. 4. If none but reall Saints may be admitted, then none but ſuch may be retained: will they then excommunicate all perſons out of their church that live without ſcandall, yet are not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly gracious?</note> Saints, ſincere beleevers, not onely having common gifts, but alſo ſaving graces, that they be not common but choice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155017:8"/>Chriſtians. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4. <hi>Anſ. to</hi> 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 69. 70. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2. 6. 21. 43. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Rob. juſt. p.</hi> 11. 38. 41. 47. 48. 61. 91. 254.</p>
               <p>Yea, convincingly ſuch, <hi>T. G.</hi> to <hi>J. G.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meek and humble ſpirits, for feare they ſhould abuſe their Church-power. <hi>E. O.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Voide of inſincere ends in ſeeking of Church-Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>If any others ſhould attempt to be admitted, the Church were bound (upon diſcovery) to repell them. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2. 3. 4. 5. 24. 33. 43. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 5. The reaſon of which is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, leſt they take an harlot into the boſome of Chriſt in ſtead of a chaſte Spouſe.</p>
               <p>If any ſuch be admitted they are not true but falſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Church may conſiſt of none but reall Saints, ſo farre as in them lies, they hold the Church is bound to make<note n="i" place="margin">Admit it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>ad eſſe eccleſiae</hi> that all the members ſhould be really holy, yet ſtill the queſtion might be by what rule wee ſhould eſtimate that their holineſſe; whether by the rule of a large charitie which beleeveth and hopeth all things, judging all them to be ſanctified that doe not give convincing and unqueſtionable proofe of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or of a ſtrict ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting none to be ſo, but ſuch as give convincing and unqueſtionable proof that they are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? And whether in this inquirie the church is to accept of all faire overtures and ſhewes of Grace, in ſuch as offer themſelves, as ſufficient, for the preſent, to admiſſion, or muſt more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly ſearch and ſound mens hearts to the bottome? ſeeing the Scripture ſaith to a particular perſon, If thy brother ſay it repenteth me, thou ſhalt forgive him. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether the ſame rule will not by proportion reach alſo to a whole Church? and ſo by conſequent to church-admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? neither doe we read of any ſuch ſtrict examination, in admiſſion of members, mentioned in Scriptures, but that men were accepted upon very eaſie and generall termes. The reaſon why they keep their Church-doores ſo cloſe ſhut, is good and plauſible in it ſelf, but applyed to this courſe ſeemes to caſt an aſperſion upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that hath made no ſuch rule of prevention, and upon the Apoſtles and their Churches which practiſed none ſuch that ever we read of; and ſeemes to be both againſt charitie, that ſuſpects no evill; and againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian wiſdome too; For whether is it a greater hurt to the Church to admit of ſome (yea many) hypocrites, or to keepe out of the Church (through ſuch unwarranted ſcrupuloſitie) ſome (though but one, or a few) ſincere Chriſtians? yea, againſt Juſtice too, 1. In reſpect of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites whom and their children to exclude from outward Church-priviledges (if God have not excluded them) is much more in jurious then to pull the clothes off their backes, or their meat out of their mouthes. 2. Eſpecially to ſome ſincere Chriſtians and their infants, as it may fall out, to whom by all right, both before God and men, Church-ordinances doe belong, who yet by this ſtrictneſſe are defrauded of the ſame.</note> ſtrict inquirie, and take exact triall of all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are to be admitted into Church-fellowſhip: yea, ſo much and ſo long, as untill they have throughly approved their ſinceritie. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 10. <hi>Anſ. to</hi> 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 70.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155017:8"/>
                  <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2. 43. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 5. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> This laſt giveth this advice to his friend intending to goe over. Above all things let thoſe that come to <hi>N. E.</hi> ſearch their eſtate well towards God, and make their calling ſure before they come. For if men come to offer themſelves to be members of any Church here, their evidences will be then viewed and ſcanned, and ſearch will be made what they can ſay for themſelves to ſhew both their cutting off from ſin and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing into Chriſt; and many other ſuch warnings from thence we have had.</p>
               <p>See <hi>Barr. diſc. p.</hi> 33. <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 255. 256. <hi>Rob. Apol. p.</hi> 81. <hi>Can. neceſs. of ſeparation. p.</hi> 167.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In which triall they uſe to require, firſt,<note n="k" place="margin">Doubtleſſe any of theſe trials may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, with the warrant of Scripture, ſo that they be not extended beyond due meaſure: As 1. if all ſhould be required to concur els no admiſſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as wee ſee men in Scripture have bin ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Church-co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion upon ſome one of them onely, as <hi>Paul, act.</hi> 9. upon <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> his teſtimonie alone. And <hi>Phebe, Ron.</hi> 16.1. upon <hi>Pauls</hi> teſtimonie, And (where other teſtimonie is wanting) Experience alone of ones blameleſſe converſation, for a reaſonable time (where there is nothing to the contrary) may ſeeme a ſufficient argument of his ſinceritie, to a Scripture charitie, that is not ſuſpicious, thinketh no evill, but takes all things (that well it may) in the beſt part. 2. If in examining of mens knowledge and opinion in points of Religion more ſhould be abſolutely required then the leaſt meaſure, and that in meer fundamentals only.</note> Letters of recommendations from other Churches or perſons abſent. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 28. 29. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Teſtimonie of their own members preſent, if there be any that know the parties. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 1. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Experience of their Converſation amongſt themſelves: In taking up of which Experience ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the time is long, if other teſtimonials bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155017:9"/>
                  <hi>E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, They examine them touching their knowledge in the Principles of Religion. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to. 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Though ſome or all the fore-named proofes be given, yet they confide not therein, nor can be ſatisfied therewith, without a<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Whether (when the other foure have preceded) 1. this addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be not ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the other being ſufficient to a right qualified charitie. 2. Whether (if the other foure ſerve not) this be not bootleſſe and ineffectuall. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if the party to be admitted be not diſcovered unſound by any of the other trials, then either he is ſound indeed, or elſe a ſubtle hypocrite, which if he be, then he will deceive the Church preſent as well as he hath done others abſent, and by his golden words, (wherein hypocrites uſually excell) as well or much more then by his deeds and couverſation: unleſſe we ſhould imagine (as ſome of that way here doe) that the Church hath in it ever ſuch a ſpirit of diſcerning as that it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by any. 3. Whether it be not a thing to many impoſſible, who know not the time when, much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe the manner how they were converted, or have forgotten it, or through temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation doe altogether queſtion it; And the rather conſidering 1. the manner of propounding the queſtions, which is at the pleaſure of him that propounds them: For all know they love no ſet formes. 2. The manner required in anſwering, which muſt be both publike, and <hi>ex tempore</hi> too: Not knowing what will be asked them before it be asked, and therefore not having much time to conſider what to anſwere. 3. Alſo if we conſider the matters about which the man is to be asked: which I ſhall deliver unto the Reader in ſome of their own words. <hi>I. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> ſaith, The ſpeciall things they drive at are to finde ſome degree of legall terrours, Evangelicall mourning for ſin, deſire after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and upon what Promiſe the ſoule was quieted. <hi>W. T.</hi> to Maſter <hi>B.</hi> The chiefe Points that the Church deſires to be ſatisfied in are concorning the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off from the old <hi>Adam,</hi> and a mans ingraffing into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> how the Law hath had it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worke, how the Goſpell its worke, what ſight a man hath had of ſinne, what conviction of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer erroneous wayes, what deſpaire of Salvation in and from themſelves, what throwing downe and humiliation, &amp;c? Alſo whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> be reveiled to them, in the miniſtery of the Word, or any other way? what eſteeme they have of him? what deſire to enjoy him? whether they have yet cloſed with their Redeemer in any ſweet Promiſe, or be ſtill in a waiting, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting condition, ſtaying the time when the Holy Ghoſt will ſtirre up the act of Faith, make up the union, give the aſſurance, &amp;c? The ſame hand writes. The Churches here admit none but upon confeſſion of their Faith, and an humble commemoration before God and the Church, how God hath wrought with them, and how farre and in what manner he hath gone along with them in their Vocation, &amp;c. Now (theſe things before premiſed being well conſidered) I aske again, if it be not a thing impoſſible for many good ſoules (fit for Church-Societie, and who have right to Church-ordinances) to render ſuch an account, and in ſuch manner, to the ſatisfaction of a multitude concerning the ſoundneſſe of their converſion. Yea, 4. I aske whether ſo to exact it be not a greater uſurpation and tyranny over the ſouls and conſciences of men then the Biſhops themſelves (though bad enough) did ever exerciſe? 5. If there muſt needs be ſuch an account given both of mens knowledge and grace, were in not better and ſafer that a ſet and ſtanding Rule were by common agreement made according to Gods Word, for triall of both, and this one and the ſame (for ſubſtance at leaſt) in all the Churches, durable, and to continue the ſame without variation (unleſſe upon cogent neceſſitie) written and recorded, and ſo made publike not onely to the Churches and their members who are to be meaſured thereby, but alſo to other Churches, whom it may concerne to know vvhat their Siſter-churches doe, and how they walke in the Lord. For want of ſuch a Rule, by the courſe which they uſe, many inconveniences may follow, as in the ſtronger that can ſpeake better, may grow ſpirituall pride of their own abilities, and contempt of others that are weaker. In the weaker, envie at thoſe that doe better then themſelves, and diſcouragement, being afraid to off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r themſelves to triall, becauſe they know not whether they ſhall be judged fit or no, or having offered themſelves, and repulſed, they will hardly offer themſelves againe, but rather live they and theirs out of the Church all their dayes: or being accepted and admitted, yet the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their own weakneſſe, perhaps abſurdneſſe, in delivering themſelves before ſuch a multitude, when others have done ſo farre better, and with more acceptance then themſelves, ſticking by them may much rebate the edge of that little goodneſſe that is in them. And in the whole Church, or many therein, it may occaſion partialitie, with more indulgence to ſome, and rigour to others, errours and miſtakes either on the right or left hand, either in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of divine truths, or in laying out the true and certaine evidences of Grace, yea diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and diſcord between ſeverall Churches, or the members of the ſame Church thereabout, and about the perſons admitted or repulſed, admittable or not admittable into the Church.</note> verball declaration (either made by a mans ſelfe, or elſe drawne out of him by interrogatories) touching the manner of his Converſion from point to point, and what evidences he can ſhew of the truth of his grace, of his ſound faith, and ſincere repentance. <hi>H. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> ſaith, Let none trouble himſelfe for a Certificate, it will not availe him, whoſoever he be that comes, (though the beſt knowne, and moſt eminently godly) muſt be examined, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:155017:9"/>
               <p n="6">6. This declaration is made firſt in private before either ſome of the officers, or other perſons betruſted with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of the perſons to be admitted. And after alſo in<note n="m" place="margin">Why may not the officers, or ſome prime men with them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate examination be ſufficient, and their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie ſatisfactorie to the Church for a member to be admitted, as well as for a whole Church to be approved? (as in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Of the inconveniences of bringing all things to the examination of the multitude, ſee after. It hath been informed, and is credible, that multitudes of our Engliſh in <hi>N. E.</hi> yea, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of them are there out of Church order, and ſo both they and theirs live little better then Heathens, ſome of which before they went were here reputed good folkes, and godly people: But is not this our brethrens rigour one of the cauſes thereof? If it be, they had need to have very cleare and ſound grounds for what they doe, or elſe it will be an heavie reckoning for them one day: That many amongſt them are out of the Church. See <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 33, 36. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32 <hi>queſt. p.</hi> 7. Maſter <hi>F.</hi> to <hi>I. B. E. O.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> and ſome good ones too: <hi>I. P.</hi> to <hi>W. R. A. M.</hi> to Maſter <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note> publike before all the Church (though never ſo many) and that ſo as to the conviction and ſatisfaction of them all. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 23, 24. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62. 70. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 6. <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155017:10"/>
               <p n="7">7. When any member of any of the Churches of their own way, goe from one Church to another<note n="n" place="margin">I ſee no reaſon for this difference, nor warrant for this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of members temporarie, or tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and fixed, in this caſe. If ſuch exactneſs muſt be had in the one, I ſee not why it ſhould bee diſpenſed with in the other.</note> onely as tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, or ſojourners for the time, they are admitted to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, onely bringing with them letters of recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation from their own Church. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 29. But when any ſuch member comes from one of their Churches to another to be admitted as a fixed member there, then he is not admitted (notwithſtanding any letters of recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or any other teſtimoniall or evidence whatſoever) without ſuch a new<note n="o" place="margin">By this ſtrict courſe they tell us they have ſeen much good to follow, both in the diſcovering and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiering of ſome unſound both in opinion and grace, and in the convincing, humbling, and converting of others. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 3. 35. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 69. But 1. all men know that ſucceſſe alone is not ſufficient to legitimate any courſe: 2. They tell us what good hath come thereby, but they do not tell us what evill. How many godly have been kept out of Church-Societie by this meanes, ſome becauſe they durſt not offer themſelves to triall, others becauſe they could not ſatisfie ſo curious a multitude with the evidences of their grace, and ſome becauſe they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved not the courſe, and therefore could not ſubmit unto it: But of the inconveniences of this courſe, ſee before.</note> Examination as aforeſaid, and as if he had never been examined nor admitted into Church-So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie before. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 29, 30. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2, 7, 9, 35.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Notwithſtanding all this rigour and ſtrictneſſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will aſſure us that the Churches uſe great indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in their triall, and ſtoope unto very<note n="p" place="margin">If it be the mind of God that they ſhould be ſo ſtrict, &amp; that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reaſon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> leſt they ſhould admit an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot into the boſome of Chriſt, in ſtead of a chaſt Spouſe, how can they remit any degree of that rigour, contrary to the mind of God: If it be not his mind, hovv dare men venture further into the ſearch of other mens hearts, or in poſe any thing upon their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s further then they have the mind of God to warrant them?</note> low termes, that they may take men into Church-fellowſhip. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 8. the knowne Godly are preſently admitted upon their own deſire. <hi>W. T.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> ſaith, If a man be humble, and have an earneſt deſire, though he be but in a waiting condition, if in other things he make conſcience of his wayes, he knowes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155017:10"/>no man of wit will denie him to become a member. The ſame man to <hi>P. H.</hi> If your miniſters were here, they would not think us too ſtrict, but too remiſſe in Diſcipline. I think in time we ſhall grow like old <hi>England. E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C.</hi> But of their abatements ſee after more particularly.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Thus far of the firſt (which is the maine) thing they require in perſons to be admitted into Church-fellowſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> true and reall Saintſhip. A ſecond is, that they be ſuch as can cleave together both in<note n="q" place="margin">This is very good, &amp; comfortable, when it may be had, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome differ from us in opinion, in points inferiour? may they not be admitted and tollerated in that, ſo long as they be not turbulent or infectious? And what if men be of more ſowre and cynicall diſpoſitions (by nature) muſt no body admit them into Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip? muſt they and theirs be for ever kept out of the Church, and from all Church-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and priviledges, (though they ſhould have truth of grace, as 'tis poſſible they may) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome invincible remaines of an harſh and crabbed conſtitution?</note> opinion and affection. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4. and that there be a ſutableneſſe and ſweetneſſe of ſpirit in them, apt to cloſe one with another. <hi>J. Cott.</hi> notes of the Church in <hi>fol. p.</hi> 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="10">10. A third is, that they<note n="r" place="margin">Doubtleſſe a good rule, agreeing to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Pattern, and the reaſon good: I could wiſh they that hold it forth ſo ſtrictly to others did not needleſly ſwerve from it themſelves. For whereas our Law hath tyed all men dwelling within ſuch and ſuch precincts to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſuch a place, under ſuch a Miniſterie for Gods publike worſhip and exerciſe of Church duties, ſome of them (contrary to this good Law) deſtroy theſe (ſo far forth at leaſt) orderly conſociations, pull aſunder our true (though not pure) Chriſtian Churches, and patch up others of their own making, gotten ſome from one pariſh, (yea, towne, citie) ſome from another, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many miles aſunder, and therefore ſeldome or never meeting together, but at publike worſhip, when they have both their holy-day clothes and courſes on; whereby other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are robbed of their ſheep, confuſion is bred in the Churches, the pattern of Scripture Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is forſaken, which ever deſcribes the members of each Church by the place of their coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, and (beſides other inconveniences) the maine end pretended for their ſo firme and cloſe uniting by Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> mutuall watching over each other, is utterly prevented.</note> cohabite together, as neere as may be, for their better mutuall watching one over another. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="11">11. A fourth thing is, they muſt be ſuch as know what belongs to<note n="f" place="margin">Therefore, if any man denie, or but doubt of this Church-covenant (<hi>viz.</hi> as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Covenant of Grace) their Church doores are for ever ſhut againſt him. God helpe me then.</note> Church-covenant, and approve thereof. <hi>J. P.</hi> to <hi>W. R. T. G.</hi> to <hi>J. G.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:155017:11"/>
               <p n="12">12. Laſtly, they muſt ſeeke and deſire Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Church-fellowſhip (<hi>viz.</hi> in their way of it.) <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 11.39. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4. <hi>J.W. Anſ.</hi> to 10. <hi>Queſt. J.W.</hi> to <hi>T.S. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 8. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 4. which if they doe not, they account them<note n="t" place="margin">This is harſheſt of all the reſt: may not ſuch forbearance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of humilitie, or modeſtie (though unwarrantable) ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or tenderneſſe of conſcience, as ſcrupling their covenant, and the courſes following it, diſcouragement, or the like: Men forget the royall law of love, <hi>To doe as they would be done to.</hi> Some call ſharply for charitie, Charitie, to themſelves, that ſhew but ſlender charitie to others.</note> deſpiſers of it, yea, wicked and graceleſſe perſons, and ſo unworthy of it. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 25, 26, 27, 34. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 69. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 21. <hi>J.W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt. Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>N. Concerning the admiſſion of infants, ſee after in the 7. CHAP. of Admiſſion, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Forme of the true viſible Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey hold the Forme of a true viſible Church of Chriſt is that which they call the<note n="u" place="margin">This point of church covenant is worthy of deepe conſideration, for it will touch the free-hold (not onely of our Engliſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but alſo) of all the Churches in the world, if this be the rule to try all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches by.</note> Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, whereby all the members of the Societie are united to Chriſt and one to another, which therefore they count ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſarie, eſſentiall and conſtitutive to and of the true Church. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 5-15. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 9, 39. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 6, 9, 17, 19, 20, 21, 24, 25, 38, 39. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Without this no true Church, nor true Church members, but all are harlots and concubines. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 20, 24. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 14, 18, 19, 20, 21, 24.</p>
               <p>Without it all men are without the Church, (for which they uſually cite 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.) and uncapable of any Church priviledge, <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 6, 11, 13, 19, 20, 24, 25, 27, 38, 39, 42. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Cov. p.</hi> 17, 22, 28. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11, 21, 24, 38. <hi>Anſ. to</hi> 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 69.</p>
               <p>So the Separatiſts. <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 75, 79, 56, 81, 82, 85, 86, 110, 210, 207, 231, 257, 351.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155017:11"/>
               <p n="2">2. No other tye, nor all others imaginable without this, they conceive are not ſufficient to knit men together into one Church, nor is there any other way of admiſſion into the Church but by this. Not viſible profeſſion and practiſe of truth and holineſſe (though never ſo compleat and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere.) Therefore they ſay<note n="*" place="margin">A ſtrange, yet bold, aſſertion, ſpoken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proofe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, conſent of other Authours, or good ſhew of reaſon, <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek</hi> was a Prieſt, and therefore prayed, preached, and offered ſacrifice, but did he this by himſelfe, and for himſelfe alone? Can there be a Prieſt by office, without a people?</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> (with others ſuch eminently Godly) were yet no members of the viſible Church, becauſe not within this Church covenant. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 66. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 14. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 28, 37. Nor<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Robinſ. juſtif. p.</hi> 230, ſaith, 'its an Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillicall errour to hold that Baptiſme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes the viſible Church: I ſuppoſe his ſenſe is the ſame with theirs, when they ſay that Baptiſme admits not into the viſible Church; The contrary whereunto, I conceive, is neither Popiſh nor Anabapt. but may well paſſe for Orthodoxe (as uſually it doth amongſt Divines) it we doe but diſtinguiſh between admiſſion into the <hi>Ch.</hi> reall and formall, between the ſubſtance of the thing and the ceremonie, or formalitie thereof. The ſubſtance and reall admiſſion indeed uſually goes before Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. For infants of parents within the Church, are born within the Church, and ſo really within it before they be haptized. And beleevers of age, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king open profeſſion of their faith and repentance, are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> made members of the viſible church by their viſible profeſſion. But the formall admiſſion of both in the ſolemne perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, is both acted and ſealed at once in Baptiſme, which is (as it were) a Chriſtians for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall matriculation or inrollment amongſt the members of the viſible Church. It this be not ſo, then let them tell me what and when is the formall admiſſion of infants into the viſible Church, or are they never formally admitted untill they come to age?</note> Baptiſme. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q.</hi> 12. Nor coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 14, 20. Nor voluntary and uſuall frequenting the ſame place of worſhip, ſubjecting a mans ſelfe to the ſame officers and lawes of government, nor joyning himſelfe in all holy fellowſhip both publike and private with the ſame ſocietie. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 21. Nor the law of the land made by the Magiſtrates authoritie, with our own implicite conſent in Parliament, appointing that all Profeſſours of Religion that ſit down within ſuch and ſuch precincts, ſhall be of ſuch a Societie or Church. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 14. Nor all theſe together without the Church covenant, which only is ſufficient to doe it. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 24. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Cov. p.</hi> 5, 14, 18-21, 24, 25. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 19, 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This covenant they hold to be diſtinct from the<note n="y" place="margin">Were the queſtion only of the Covenant of Grace to be either entred into, or renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again and again at the conſtitution or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Churches, the matter were ſoon at an end; that would be eaſily granted to be neceſſary, yea, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall: And ſuch on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were all the Scripture Covenants, which are uſually cited by them to prove their Church covenant. But that will not ſerve their turn. 2. Or were it of a covenant between the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and their people, I conceive, there would be no ſtrife, this being tacitely implyed in their mutuall choice each of other. You ſhall be our paſtour, &amp;c. and we will be your people; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided 1. it be not obtruded as eſſentiall, or abſolutely neceſſary to have it expreſſe. 2. that it be underſtood with a <hi>ſalvo jure,</hi> not onely to that particular church and members, nor only to that particular officer, but alſo to all other Churches, who have a common intereſt each in other, for the good of all, moſt of all to God himſelfe. 3. Yea, if it were of a covenant between the church and her members, and each member with another of remaining together as a fixed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, till death (without extraordinary impediment) as a thing in it ſelfe arbitrary and occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionall only, upon ſome particular reaſons calling for it. I ſpeake what I thinke, This alſo would not be denyed. 4. Or (which is all that can with any colour of reaſon be defined) if it were of an eccleſiaſticall conſtitution only, binding the members to the Diſcipline and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of ſuch a church (during mens convenient abode with it) as a thing expedient only for the better being and better governing of the church, I ſay, an Eccleſiaſticall conſtitution, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to generall Rules of Scripture, though not preciſely commanded therein: And which may therefore be intended, temitted, or altered <hi>pro re natâ,</hi> according to the generall Rules of Scripture at the Churches diſcretion; Such as are the covenants or promiſes required of the members of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French Churcher;</hi> There would not have been many adverſaries. But when an expreſſe vocall covenant is held forth, and with all eagerneſſe preſſed on us, and on all churches as a Divine Ordinance particularly commanded in Scripture, abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, eſſentiall and conſtitutive to a true church; without which there is no true church, but all ſocieties are whores and concubines, and without which there is no right unto, nor orderly participation of any Church dutie or ordinance: And this ſo obligatory that it is <hi>piaculum</hi> to remove from that ſocietie, with which one is in covenant, without their generall conſent, ſought at leaſt (as after is ſhewed.) And not only ſo, but alſo letters are ſent over with ſtrong lines, to diſſwade our people from living any longer in the way they have done, out of Church order, becauſe out of church covenant. Sermons are likewiſe preached, bookes printed, and private diſcourſes made, and in all theſe arguments artificially uſed, and poſſionately and perſwaſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly urged, yea, the Scriptures themſelves forced to ſpeake for their Church covenant as a Divine Ordinance, &amp;c. I ſay, when it is thus held forth and urged on us, no marvell if it be not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained without much agitation, yea, if it meet with much oppoſition, and that amongſt the godly and learned both perſons and Churches.</note> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; ſo, as that many which are within the Covenant of Grace (<hi>i.e.</hi> effectually, yea, and viſibly called too) are not within the Church Covenant, and ſo not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155017:12"/>the viſible Church, as <hi>Job, Melchizedek,</hi> &amp;c. of whom before. And again, many are within the Church covenant, and ſo within the viſible Church, that are not within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, as hypocrites in the Church. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 5, 6, 14 <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet ſometimes they tell us, it is not diſtinct altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or in ſubſtance, but in ſome reſpects onely, as a part from the whole, this being a branch of that. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 3, 7, 8, 12, 26, 28. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 8, 31, 43. A volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155017:12"/>profeſſion of<note n="z" place="margin">If this Church cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be but the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, then ſurely we have it, and renew it daily, in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, at the Lords Table, on our ſolemn Faſts, &amp;c. why call they then ſo eagerly for that we have, as if we wanted it? 2. If it be but the Covenant of Grace, what abſolute neceſſity can there be of repeating and renewing it expreſſely, and reciprocally, at every admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a new member?</note> ſubjection thereunto. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 22, 24. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 18. eſpecially to that part thereof which concernes Church<note n="a" place="margin">If it be a covenant of Church duties only, and to this ſociety only, what needs a repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole covenant of Grace, at leaſt as eſſentiall to this covenant, and to Church conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and to Church memberſhip, more then to a marriage covenant, or any other holy cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? It may be done at a wedding; true, but to make it eſſentiall to it, would marre many a lawfull marriage. Nor can it be judged eſſentiall that the particulars of the covenant of Grace, ſo farre as they concerne church duties ſhould be (and that ſo oft) repeated. If two parties intending to marry each other, ſhould doe it in this generall forme only (or the like) he ſaying to her, Ile be thy husband; and ſhe to him, Ile be thy wife, if there were no defect in the covenant, or otherwiſe; but want of mentioning the mutuall duties that by Gods law belong to married perſons, I beleeve that would never make it null: nor would that their covenant the leſſe bind them to ſuch mutuall duties, becauſe the particulars were not expreſt in the covenant at the marriage-making.</note> fellowſhip, and Church duties. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4, 7, 8, 26. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 75. with application to this particular Church<note n="b" place="margin">As this covenant is deſtructive to our Churches, ſo is it apt to cauſe ſchiſmes and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of one Church from another even amongſt themſelves. Its a partition wall (as one cals it) built up to hinder that communion that ought to be among Churches, and that care that one Church and member ought to have of another. Here being ſo ſtrict a tye to the duties belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to our own Church, and the members thereof, but not a word of any dutie to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to other Churches, or their members. So that if a member of the ſame Church with my ſelfe want watching, counſell, reproofe, &amp;c. my covenant binds me to performe accordingly. But if one of another Church doe need as much, and I have fit opportunitie, &amp;c. yet by this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant I have nothing to doe with him, he is without to me, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.</note> onely, to which one is now to be joyned by this covenant. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 10, 15, 28. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 75.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And this covenant is made by every member, both with God, and the Church, and by the Church alſo backe againe with every member. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4, 10, 12. <hi>J.W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>quest. R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. And thus they define it.<note n="c" place="margin">All the middle part of this definition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines the matter of a true Church: Of which in the former Chapter: onely the beginning and end doe ſhew the nature of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (which they call the Forme) of which here in this Chapter.</note> 'Its a ſolemne and publike Promiſe before the Lord and his people, whereby a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Chriſtians called (by the power and mercie of God)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155017:13"/>to the fellowſhip of Chriſt, and (by his providence) to dwell together, and (by his Grace) to love and cleave together in the unitie of faith and brotherly love, and deſirous to partake (according to the will of God) in all the holy Ordinances of God together in one Congregation, doe bind themſelves to the Lord to walke in all ſuch<note n="d" place="margin">The words are good and faire; but he that takes this covenant had need to conſider that in the ſenſe of them that give it, The waies of God, are their wayes of Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and popular Government, which if he be not upon good ground ſatisfied that they are indeed the wayes of God, then how can he ſafely ingage himſelfe to them by this covenant, and that not only to be a patient, to tolerate what he cannot mend, but even to act with them alſo in the ſame? Our brethren conceive that a Miniſter in ſwearing canonicall obedience, <hi>in omnibus licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> to a Biſhop, did thereby juſtifie Epiſcopacie; And doe not by the ſame reaſon, all that take this covenant juſtifie popularitie and independencie.</note> wayes of holy worſhip to him, and of edification one towards another, as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath required in his word of every Church of Chriſt and the members thereof. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 5. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 3. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The properties hereof: 1. It is ſacred not civill. <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Cov. p.</hi> 3, 4. 2. It muſt be publike before all the Church. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 4, 17, <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi> 3. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and expreſſe. <hi>J.W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt. Apol. p.</hi> 45. 4. So firmely binding, as that it cannot be looſed without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Church. Of which ſee more after.</p>
               <p n="8">8. After all this rigourous exacting of this Covenant, ſometimes they mollifie the matter, and tell us, That an<note n="e" place="margin">If ſo little wil ſerve, what need ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries for more, and the truth of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be queſtioned, ſuch ſharpe contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt brethren to be raiſed, and ſad ſeparations of one Church and Chriſtian from another to be made about and for want of an expreſſ covenant as eſſentiall and abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Church eſtate?</note> agreement or conſent to be members of this or that ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to walk with them in Church fellowſhip will ſerve and is equivalent. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 32, 44. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 21, 22, 23. <hi>T.G.</hi> to <hi>J.G.</hi> And ſometimes in ſtead of exacting this covenant, they onely inquire what is mens intention, whether they intend to doe ſo or no, and if they intend it, that ſufficeth. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>P.</hi> And as for us, they ſometimes acknowledge, that ourconſent to the law of the land made by King and Parliament, appointing that all ſuch as ſit down within ſuch precincts, ſhall be of this or that Pariſh or Church, is an implicite covenant. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 14. and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that our promiſe to beleeve &amp; walk according to our Articles of Religion is ſufficient. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 40.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:155017:13"/>
               <p n="9">9. This Covenant amongſt them, though for ſubſtance of matter it be all one, in all their Churches, yet in forme of words it is divers in divers Churches, but in the ſame Church it is ever in one and the ſame<note n="f" place="margin">Here we have a ſet forme of holy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the Church, (a principall part of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) invented by one or more men (perhaps of a former age) and impoſed upon others, even as many as ſhall enter into that Church, read alſo upon a book; And what is this better or more lawfull then ſuch a ſet forme of Prayer, eſpecially ſince this covenant is impoſed as an Ordinance of God, and abſolutely neceſtarie, ſo as no book prayer is, And ſeeing the matter is confeſt to be all one in all Churches, why may not the forme alſo be lawfully all one by mutuall agreement; And if one forme of covenant be lawfull for all the Churches conſociated? why not one forme of Leitourgy, or Directorie for worſhip alſo?</note> Forme of words, as well as matter, and therefore put in writing, and when any one is admitted it is then read, either by the party himſelfe that is admitted, or elſe unto him by ſome other man, whereunto he is to give his aſſent. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R. Apol. p.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="10">10. One or two of their formes I will here inſert, that the Reader may the better by example take up their ſenſe touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Covenant.</p>
               <p>1. The Covenant of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church at <hi>Roter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame</hi> (as is reported to us) renewed when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.P.</hi> was made their Paſtour, was to this effect.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE whoſe names are here-under written, having a long time found by ſad experience how uncomfortable it is to walk in a diſordered and unſetled condition, &amp;c. <hi>1.</hi>
                        <note n="g" place="margin">All things in theſe two formes, in a fait conſtruction, are very good, but ſome things are ſubject to an harſh conſtruction: as, where they promiſe to ſubmit to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Diſcipline without murmuring, <hi>i.e.</hi> as ſome would thinke without complaining: But what if he receive wrong, may he not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly complain either to his owne Church, or to the neighbour Churches for redreſſe? Eſpecially that clauſe ſeemes to be of a very large extent, where they promiſe to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches advice for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and theirs, as occaſion ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented: which will reach (if extended to the utmoſt) not only to reſtrain their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of removall from that Church, without their conſent (which yet were too much) but alſo in other things, as in marrying a mans daughter, changing a mans ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, taking a journey, making a bargain, &amp;c. 2. Here are many good duties promiſed, and ſins proteſted againſt, but the moſt of them are common to all men, at leaſt to all Chriſtians (not to Church-members only.) But by the ſame reaſon that its needfull and uſefull to expreſſe theſe particulars, 'its needfull and uſefull to expreſſe many more: as they proteſt againſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, idleneſſe and earthly cares, may they not as juſtly adde non-payment of debts, waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe by pride, apparell, and riot in wines, and the like? 3. The former covenant mentions little or nothing of that for which the Church-covenant is ſo preſſed as eſſentiall, &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> Church-fellowſhip in Church-duties with approptiation to this particular Church: And may be as ſit at a wedding as at the conſtitution of a viſible Church, for ought I know. 4. The latter tyes ſtrictly to duties to their own Church, but no word of watching over, admoniſhing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting, releeving the members of other Churches, or Chriſtians that are no members. Charitie, they ſay, begins at home, but it ſhould not ſtay there. It ſeekes not its own things only, but alſo the good of its neighbour, of as many as poſſibly it can.</note> Doe renue our Covenant in Baptiſme, and avouch God to be our God. <hi>2.</hi> We reſolve to cleave to the true and pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, oppoſing to our power all falſe wayes. <hi>3.</hi> We will not allow our ſelves in any known ſin, but will renounce it, ſo ſoon as it is manifested from Gods Word ſo to be: the Lord lending us power. <hi>4.</hi> We reſolve to carry our ſelves in our ſeverall places of government and obedience with all good conſcience, knowing we must give an account to God. <hi>5.</hi> We will labour for further growth in grace, by hearing, reading, prayer, meditation, and all other wayes we can. <hi>6.</hi> We meane not to over-burthen our hearts with earthly cares, which are the bane of all holy duties, the breach of the Sabbath, and the other Commandements. <hi>7.</hi> We will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and meekly ſubmit to Chriſtian Diſcipline, without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155017:14"/>murmuring, and ſhall labour ſo to continue, and will ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be more forward, zealous, faithfull, loving and wiſe in admoniſhing others. <hi>8.</hi> We will labour by all our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for the furtherance of the Gospell as occaſion ſhall be offered to us. <hi>9.</hi> We promiſe to have our children, ſervants, and all our charge taught the wayes of God. <hi>10.</hi> We will ſtrive to give no offence to our brethren by cenſuring them raſhly by ſuspitions, evill ſpeakings, or any other way. <hi>11.</hi> Laſtly, we doe protest not onely againſt open and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins, as drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, &amp;c. but alſo againſt evill companie, and all appearance of evill to the utmost of our power.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Per me</hi> F.H.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>2. The Covenant of the Church of Chriſt at Salem was renewed to this effect.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE whoſe names are here-under written,<note place="margin">5. We have in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in ſpeaking in publike, or ſcrupling: By which it appeares that they are allowed (when called) pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely both to ſpeake (that is as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, to prophecie) and to ſcruple (that is, to propound queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, make objections, &amp;c.) elſe what need a law to reſtrain them from doing it uncal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? And if it were not for ſome ſuch law to reſtrain them, there muſt needs be much conſuſion where each member hath equall power, if he had equal liberty to exerciſe that power when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But what differs this law (in force) from an Eccleſiaſticall Canon? but that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons are now grown out of requeſt, that Church Covenants may bee the better cryed up.</note> members of the preſent Church of Chriſt at Salem, &amp;c. ſolemnly in the preſence of God, &amp;c. renew that Church Covenant which we find this Church bound unto at their firſt beginning, <hi>viz.</hi> We covenant with the Lord, and one with another, and do binde our ſelves in the preſence of God to walk together in all the wayes of God, according as he is pleaſed to reveale himſelfe to us in his Word. And doe more explicitely in the fear of the Lord profeſſe and proteſt to walk as followeth.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155017:14"/>
                        <hi>1.</hi> We avow the Lord to be our God, and our ſolves his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the truth and ſimplicitie of our ſpirits. <hi>2.</hi> We give up our ſelves to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the word of his Grace, for the teaching, ſanctifying, and ruling of us in matters of worſhip and converſation, reſolving to cleave to him alone for life and glorie, and oppoſe all contrary wayes, canons and conſtitutions of men in his worſhip. <hi>3.</hi> We promiſe to walk with our brethren and ſiſters in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation with all watchfulneſſe, and tenderneſſe, avoiding all jealouſies, ſuſpitions, backbitings, cenſurings, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, ſecret riſings of ſpirit againſt them, but in all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to follow the rule of the Lord Jeſus, to bear and forbear, give and forgive, as he hath taught us. <hi>4.</hi> In publike or private we will willingly do nothing to the offence of our Church, but will be ready to take advice for our ſelves and ours, as occaſion ſhall be preſented. <hi>5.</hi> We will not in the Congregation be forward either to ſhew our own gifts or parts in ſpeaking, or ſcrupling, or there to diſcover the failings of our brethren or ſiſters,<note place="margin">6. In this latter alſo here is a ſtrict tye or bond of walking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and mutuall watchfulneſſe, one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver another: But how can they do that, that live farre aſunder, and never ſee one another but at publike mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings? and ſome of them that live ſome thouſands of miles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, and perhaps being Miniſters of Churches there, yet accept of fixed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, even the charge of ſoules here. How can theſe watch over one another?</note> but attend an orderly call thereunto: knowing how much the Lord may be diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp;c. by our diſtempers, and weakneſſes in publike. <hi>6.</hi> We binde our ſelves to ſtudie the advancement of the Goſpell in all truth and peace, both in regard of thoſe that are within and without, no way ſlighting our Siſter-churches, but uſing their counſell, as need ſhall be, not laying a ſtumbling block before any. <hi>7.</hi> We hereby promiſe to carry our ſelves in all lawfull obedience to thoſe that are ſet over us in Church and Common-wealth, knowing how wel-pleaſing it will be to the Lord, &amp;c. <hi>8.</hi> We reſolve to approve our ſelves to the Lord in our particular callings, ſhunning idleneſſe as the bane of any ſtate, nor will we deal hardly or oppreſſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with any. <hi>9.</hi> We will alſo to our best abilities teach our children and ſervants the knowledge of the Lord, and his will, that they may ſerve him alſo.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>O. H.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p n="11">11. This Covenant (thus diſtinguiſhed from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace) they hold to be that Covenant which is<note n="h" place="margin">Here is a piece or two of ſuch Divinitie as I never heard or read before: but <hi>uno abſurdo dato, mille ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:155017:15"/>ſealed by the Sacraments, and for the ſealing and ratifying of which the Sacraments were principally ordained of God, and therefore to be adminiſtred only to ſuch as are firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this Covenant, as ſeales thereof. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 15, 19, 31. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 63, 66. And therefore, that ſuch perſons as (by their condition) cannot joyne in Church Covenant, nor live in Church fellowſhip with a ſet ſocietie, are not bound to partake in Sacraments. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 39, 41.</p>
               <p>See <hi>Robinſ. juſtif. p.</hi> 80, 110. Though I doe not find the <hi>Brownists</hi> ſo ſolicitouſly to diſtinguiſh between the Church covenant, and the covenant of Grace, as theſe our brethren doe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Such as were admitted into their Churches infants by the covenant of their parents, are not yet permitted to receive the Lords Supper, when they come to yeares, untill they have firſt run through all the foreſaid courſe of<note n="i" place="margin">What if upon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation they prove nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vincingly gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as wanting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected evidences, nor yet openly ſcandalous, as being over-powred with Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and good educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and government? what ſhall become of them then, admitted as members to the Lords Supper they ſhall not be; and excommunicated, I trow, they cannot juſtly be; By this rule they muſt remain in a middle condition, neither of the Church, nor without the Church; And what warrant have we for this?</note> publike and private examination, profeſſion of faith, declaration of the manner of their converſion, and perſonall, vocall, expreſſe entring into the ſame covenant, as others of yeares have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them done, and as if they had never been received mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers before. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the manner of their firſt erecting of a viſible Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1.<note n="k" place="margin">The Reader may perhaps think (in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe two firſt articles) ſome fault to be in the collectour, that ſo foule a contradiction ſhould be held; but if there be any fault, it muſt be none but their owne, either in holding and practiſing things in themſelves ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, or elſe in reporting to us ſuch things as they neither hold nor practiſe: But this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction will yet appeare more foule, when we conſider what will after follow, that they hold it not only lawfull to do it without their conſent, but alſo ſometimes neceſſary to do it againſt their conſent: of which ſee Chap. 15.</note> ANy ſmall number (almoſt) of perſons (ſo fitted as before) they hold, may lawfully unite themſelves
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155017:15"/>into a Church body, by entring into the Church covenant aforeſaid; and ſo may conſtitute themſelves a true viſible Church of Chriſt, without any authoritative conſent of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate (ſuppoſing there be one) or of the neighbouring Churches or their Miniſters. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 43.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robinſ. juſtif. p.</hi> 181, 182.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet a<note n="l" place="margin">The law doubtleſſe is good, as from the Magiſtrate: but how doth this agree with that opinion (which too many of them amongſt us that run the ſame Church-courſes with theſe brethren hold) that the Magiſtrate hath nothing to doe with the firſt Table, unleſſe the publike peace be broken, he is to force no man againſt his conſcience too or fro, but leave every man to follow his own light and religion? Alſo as it is an agreement of the Churches and Miniſters, I the rather like it, becauſe it ſeemes to amount to little leſſe in ſubſtance then a compound Presbyterie ſet up amongſt them; the rather, if we adde what the ſame <hi>H.P.</hi> tels us, that they have alſo agreed amongſt themſelves that no man ſhall preach or vent any new or uncouth tenents, untill he have firſt communicated them with the neighbouring miniſters. A very good Canon, eſpecially for theſe times wherein men run a madding after novelties, and niceties, under the falſe pretence of a new light, and new truthes.</note> Law is made in their generall Court (civill) that no Church ſhall be there ſet up, without the knowledge of the Magiſtrate, and neighbour Churches. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi> yea, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.P.</hi> informeth us, not without the conſent of five or ſix of the neighbouring Churches at the leaſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The<note n="m" place="margin">Here is another Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall canon in act, though not in rule. If this be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the firſt erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Church, that each ſhould try and know others ſpirits, why not alſo after at the admiſſion of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member, he to try and know their ſpirits as well as they his?</note> perſons intending to enter into Church eſtate, doe before hand often meet privately amongſt themſelves to be inwardly acquainted with each others ſpirits, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring, praying together, and mutually examining each other, untill they have approved themſelves to one anothers conſciences in the ſight of God: Which when they have throughly done in private, then they agree together to enter into a church eſtate. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi> | <hi>H.W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Which before they doe, notice is given thereof to the Magiſtrate, and neighbouring Churches, that ſo ſuch as pleaſe may be preſent at the time and place thereunto appointed. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi> | <hi>H.W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> | <hi>J.W.</hi> to <hi>T.S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The number wherewith they uſually begin at the firſt conſtitution of every Church, is about 7.8. or 9. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Notice being given, the Magiſtrate and Churches ſend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155017:16"/>their<note n="n" place="margin">Here then Churches uſe meſſengers or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties to repreſent themſelves, and to act in their roome, why not in a Synod as well? And if they may truſt their power with their meſſengers for approving or diſapproving whole Churches, much more of particular members at their admiſſion.</note> Meſſengers or Deputies to ſee how things are carried, and to give them advice, direction, approbation, or diſappro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, as they ſhall ſee cauſe. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The day appointed is kept with faſting and prayer, and ſometimes (if not alwayes) preaching of the Word, which is performed by ſome of the perſons that now come to be combined into this Church-ſocietie. In the latter end of the day, each of thoſe perſons now to be churched (if I may ſo ſay) maketh publike profeſſion of his faith, thereby ſhewing his knowledge, and opinion in the Grounds and Principles of Religion, and declaring from point to point the work of God upon his ſoule in his Converſion. And all this in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporarie (at leaſt) conceived ſpeech, <hi>i. e.</hi> not in any ſet forme. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Which when the Meſſengers of the Magiſtrate and Churches have heard and conſidered, if they be unſatisfied, (or any ſtander by) they make their objections, or propound further queſtions, as they thinke fit, untill they be<note n="o" place="margin">Its an hard taske to ſatisfie all commers touching theſe things, queſtioning and obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting what they pleaſe, and harder for a man to be ſtayed perhaps for ſome differences about Church Diſcipline, or ſuppoſe ſome objection be made againſt his life, it muſt here be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and openly declared, and ſcanned before all the countrey. This is little wiſedome, leſſe charitie.</note> ſatisfied, if it may be. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. If in the end the ſaid Meſſengers be not ſatisfied, then they or ſo many of them, as concerning whom they are not ſatisfied, either in point of knowledge or grace, are forbidden to enter into Church eſtate, and ſo remaine ſtill, as before, out of the pale of the Church. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. If at length they be fully ſatisfied, and all doubts clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then the ſaid perſons proceed to enter into Church-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which being written one of them reads, and all of them ſubſcribe it, and ſo they are become a true<note n="p" place="margin">If ſo much time and ſo many encumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be needful to joyn 7. or 8. together into one church, how much time would be requiſite to joyn 3000. together. But our brethren will acknowledge the Apoſtles went a ſhorter way to work. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 29, 30. the reaſon whereof they render, becauſe the Church was not then ſubject to ſo many hypocrites: which is more then any man knowes, when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Many are called, few choſen.</hi> Many ſeeke, but few ſinde. Beſides, this courſe is uſed by our brethren not to ordinary Chriſtians only, but to the moſt godly and beſt approved. I beleeve therefore it was rather, becauſe the Holy Ghoſt had given them no ſuch direction, nor was this manner of church conſtitution then hatcht.</note> conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted viſible Church, as they ſay. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:155017:16"/>
               <p n="11">11. Which being done the ſaid Meſſengers of the other Churches give them the right hand of fellowſhip, and owne them for a ſiſter Church. And ſo returning backe doe make report to the Churches that ſent them, of all things done, and declare to them that they are to account of them as of a true Church of Chriſt. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Church-power, or the power of the Keyes, the firſt ſubject in whom it reſides, and the exerciſe of it in generall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey hold that every ſuch companie (as aforeſaid) though never ſo ſmall, conſiſting of private perſons only (<hi>i.e.</hi> ſuch as are in no church-office,) and perhaps all illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate too, yet is rightly and immediately intituled to all the priviledges of the viſible Church of Chriſt, and inveſted with all Eccleſiaſticall<note n="q" place="margin">Who would not long to be ſoon chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in this way, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately they might be indued with ſo vaſt a power? This is a ſweet morſell, no marvell if peoples teeth water for it. But where or when did God ſo grant all this power over to the people, that yet he excepted the Sacraments, and them only out of the charter? ſurely either he gave them all or none. The neceſſitie of which conſequence ſome Browniſts perceiving, therefore of late (here in <hi>London</hi>) have claimed and contended for them alſo. The word and Sacraments (in our Saviours commiſſion) are knit together, <hi>Goe preach and baptiſe,</hi> and both ſettled upon the Miniſterie. But our brethren have here divided them, and made preaching common to the people: And though our brethren intend not ſo, yet in event poſſibly this may nouriſh in the vulgar ſome fragment of poperie, as if the Sacraments were more excellent then the preaching of the Word, they being reſerved as peculiar to the Miniſters, this common to others with them.</note> power from Chriſt, as the firſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per receptacle thereof, have the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven committed to them, and may now forthwith admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and partake of all church-ordinances (except onely
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155017:17"/>Sacraments) execute all Church-cenſures, and tranſact all their owne buſineſſes within themſelves. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 10. 41, 44, 48, 49, 50. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 10. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R. R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 4. | <hi>J. W.</hi> anſ. to. 10. <hi>quest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 106, 107, 112, 121, 122, 125, 126, 127, 138, 190, 113, 167, 184, 198, 331. Sions royall prerog. Preface. <hi>Barr. diſcov. p.</hi> 39.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The particular ſorts of which Church buſineſſes are theſe. 1. Admiſſion of more members into their Societie. 2. Authoritative admonition of members offending. 3. Bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and excommunicating of ſuch as having offended prove incorrigible. 4. Looſing and authoritative forgiving ſuch as upon admonition and excommunication do repent, re-accepting them into the communion of the Church again. 5.<note n="r" place="margin">How weake good people are and inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient without their guides aſſiſtance, to examine Miniſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, to judge of Doctrines, and other matters touching per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the exerciſe of Church-government, he that pleaſe may ſee in our brethrens late Apologeticall narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, p. 24, 28. Beſides, the experience of the <hi>Boſtoners</hi> in <hi>N. E.</hi> who generally would have choſen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wheel-right</hi> (the notorious Familiſt) to have been co-teacher with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>C.</hi> there, had not ſome few withſtood it, as <hi>I. P.</hi> told <hi>W. R.</hi>
                  </note> Making, <hi>i.e.</hi> examining, electing, and with impoſition of hands ordaining their Paſtours, and all other their officers. 6. Unmaking, <hi>i.e.</hi> degrading and depoſing them again, when they ſee cauſe ſo to do. 7. Preaching, <hi>i.e.</hi> expounding and applying the word with all authoritie to the ſeverall uſes of their members. 8. And generally whatſoever elſe may concerne the edification and ſpirituall good of that ſocietie (ſave onely the adminiſtration of the ſeales.) And all this before they have any officers, or if they have any, yet without reference to them as officers at all. 9. And when they have Miniſters then they have Sacraments too. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 10, 15, 41, 42, 44, 45, 48, 49, 50, 68. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 10, 11, 12. <hi>Diſ-courſe of Cov. p.</hi> 23. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62, 70, 76, 77. <hi>J. W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt. R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 4. | <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R. Apol. p.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 9, 111.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All which things they claime to themſelves power to doe without any<note n="ſ" place="margin">When officers are not yet ſetled in any Church, or being once ſetled do fail through caſualtie, it is agreed upon on all hands that ſome extraordinary courſe is to be taken. Let it therfore be conſidered whether it be not more proper and neerer to the ordinary rule, to call in the aſſiſtance of the officers of ſome neighbouring churches (by vertue of that communion of Churches which themſelves acknowledge) to ſupply the wan: of their owne officers in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ordination, and depoſition of Miniſters, &amp;c. rather then to uſe meere private perſons, i.e. non-officers of the ſame Church?</note> authoritative concurrence or aſſiſtance of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155017:17"/>any other Churches or their officers, which they hold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull in others to offer, and in themſelves to accept or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 41. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 335, 339.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Therefore they ordinarily convene together (before they have any officers) and hold publike Eccleſiaſticall mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and execute all Eccleſiaſticall duties and offices<note n="t" place="margin">Hereby it comes to paſſe that becauſe oft-times their Churches are long without Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that they are alſo long without Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, both the Lords Supper for the elder people, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme for their infants.</note> (Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments only excepted) by meere lay men, that neither are, nor perhaps ever ſhall be officers in the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Church (being thus inveſted with all Church-power) deriveth part thereof upon her officers, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo much as ſhe cannot conveniently execute her ſelfe, and the reſt ſhe keeps ſtill in her own hands and executes accordingly. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 57. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. Diſc. p.</hi> 223.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The officers have no power in Church matters, but what the Church deriveth on them, and which ſhe may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, and reſume unto her ſelfe, if ſhe conceive they doe not uſe it well. <hi>Ibid.</hi> And therefore ſhe may call them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for their actions, though they were even Apoſtles themſelves. <hi>J. Cott.</hi> on 5. viall. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The officers are all but the Churches<note n="u" place="margin">Where ſaith the Scripture that the Church ſhould rule her officers, and the officers obey the church? we find that officers are called ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and people are commanded to obey them in the Lord fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. Heb. 13.17. but the other we never find. We find indeed the Apoſtles call themſelves the ſervants of the Church, as Chriſt alſo made himſelfe ſervant unto all, but that is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood properly, but metaphorically, and by way of ſome ſimilitude, unto ſervants, who (it good) do ſeek their maſters good, and are for their profit not their own; ſo did Chriſt and all the Apoſtles ſeek the Churches good, not their own, and ſo all Chriſtians are commanded to ſerve each other in love; But we may not thence conclude that therefore every Chriſtian is in peoprietie to be anothers ſervant, for then who ſhould be maſter? much leſſe that the Apoſtles were properly the ſervants of the Church, who gave rules to the Church what to doe, and how to walk, but received none from the Church, leaſt of all that Chriſt was ſo, who both was and is the head of that body, and King of that Kingdome. We read alſo that Miniſters are to do the acts of their miniſterie in the Name of Chriſt, and by his power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. But that they act in the name of the Church, or by the power of the Church, ſuch phraſes we do not reade them, and therefore we do not beleeve them.</note> ſervants in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie of ſpeech, and ſhe is the miſtreſſe, the queene. In all things ſhe hath the power of decreeing, and they with her, as others, the meaneſt members of the Societie: but as Miniſters, ſo they are only as her mouth to ſpeake and her hand to act
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155017:18"/>what ſhe decrees, doing all things for her, by her power, and in her name. <hi>Ibid.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>N.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. Apol. p.</hi> 49. <hi>Rob. justif. p.</hi> 121, 122, 138, 166, 178, 180, 185, 303, 322.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The<note n="x" place="margin">And this were well too, if this ſervice of the Church were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved only and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely to the officers, but alas, this is but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to them with other members. For, if either the officers be not, or be abſent, or refuſe (through ſcruple of conſcience perhaps) to act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their mind, they will (and they hold they lawfully may) call forth any other member whom they judge fit, and enable him with their power to doe all that which their officers ſhould have done: Sacraments only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</note> acts which they aſcribe unto the officers, are ſuch as theſe: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. To declare unto their people the mind of God in any matter, to adviſe, counſell, exhort, reprove, &amp;c. 2. To moderate in Church meetings, that order may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by propounding of things to be debated, gathering of voyces, pronouncing the ſentence accordingly. 3. To exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all the Churches decrees, in admiſſion of members, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of miniſters, admonition, excommunication, &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 57. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 3, 10. <hi>Cott.</hi> on viall 5. <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 9, 111, 114, 116, 121. <hi>Cannes</hi> neceſſ. of ſeparation, <hi>p.</hi> 135.</p>
               <p n="9">9.<note n="y" place="margin">This body is all eye, and all tongue, no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of members, all governours, none to be governed. All tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers contrary to the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Are all teachers?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9. And if their reaſons for this be well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, it will appeare they make as much for women to rule, as men. No marvell then if this be ſo that they complaine in print and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that Miniſters are ſlighted amongſt them, yea, trampled upon by ſome, <hi>Cott.</hi> on vial ſecond, <hi>p.</hi> 24. Maſter <hi>H.</hi> to <hi>S. A.</hi> They profeſſe to condemne Morellian and popular Government, but what can be more popular then this, wherein all have equall power to decree, and any of them may be uſed to act as well as the officers, and the officers are uſed as meer ſervants to the body, which is the Miſtreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: At moſt they are but as the Speaker in the houſe of Parliament, or as a Moderator in a Synod, which rule not but are rather ruled.</note> Every member of the Societie, that is of yeares (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept women) hath equall power with other, even with the miniſters themſelves (as they conceive) in propounding, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating, objecting, anſwering, and in judicially decreeing, and giving ſentence in all matters of the Church, whether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to faith or manners, doctrine or practiſe whatſoever. <hi>W. T.</hi> to <hi>P. H.</hi> | M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>W.</hi> letter to a friend. | <hi>Anſ. to</hi> 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 44.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. refut.</hi> of <hi>Giff. p.</hi> 81. and in his <hi>Diſcov. p.</hi> 36, 38, 125, 223. <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 9, 111, 121. Sions royall Prerog. Preface.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And therefore although the officers may lawfully prepare matters in private for the Churches hearing, yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155017:18"/>they hold all things ought to have a full publike debate in the<note n="z" place="margin">This popular go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment makes good ſtore of work both for Miniſters and people, eſpecially if the body be numerous, as the Apoſtolicall Churches were, and ours ought to be (if conveniently they may) and if they muſt all conveene in one Congregation, to he are, examine and debate all matters till all be ſatisfied, and brought to one unanimous vote. It will not be one houre or two in a weeke, nor in every day of the weeke, nor ſearce all the whole weeks time that will ſuffice to finiſh all buſineſſes that may fall out. And what time ſhall the Miniſters then have for ſtudie and other duties, or the people to follow their worldly callinge? This courſe ſeemes neither agreeable to the wiſedome of God, nor profitable to the weale of the Church. Beſides, the time of keeping their courts (on the Sabbath day) ſeemes many wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient: It muſt needs tire men out (both Miniſters and people) make them forgetfull of what they have heard, neglective of private and domeſticall duties, fill their heads and tongues full of worldly diſcourſes, and their hearts of carnall paſſions and diſtempers, all which are enemies to the right obſervation of the Lords day. <hi>Object.</hi> They finde no ſuch inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, their Churches have few offenders, and when they have, matters are ſoon diſpatched. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may well be, now whiles their choice materials romaine, and their numbers are ſo ſmall and inconſiderable, but when their Churches ſhall grow numerous, and their materials (in proceſſe of time) ſhall degenerate, as they muſt needes, will not theſe inconveniences, and many more follow then?</note> preſence of the whole Societie, that ſo they may be able to give their ſentence in faith. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 31. <hi>J. C.</hi> printed let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>p.</hi> 4. which is therefore uſually done on the Sabbath day after Evening Sermon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea, <hi>p.</hi> 307. <hi>Rob. apol. p.</hi> 38.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether matters be carried amongſt them by moſt voyces or no, is not ſo generally agreed upon. Some affirme that the major part carries it againſt the leſſer part, yea, though the officers be in this leſſer part, and do ſhew ſtrong reaſon to the contrary. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>M.</hi> to <hi>J. M.</hi> Others, that the whole body muſt agree elſe nothing proceeds. <hi>J. P.</hi> to <hi>W. R. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 60, 61. Some, that things are not carried by voyces at all, but by<note n="a" place="margin">The queſtion here it not what ought to be done <hi>in foro conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entie, &amp; divino,</hi> but <hi>in foro eccleſie, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno.</hi> It will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on all hands that all things in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall (as civill) Court, ought to be done according to truth and right. But ſuppoſing a difference do ariſe, and both ſides pretend to truth and right; (our brethren deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any others to interpoſe otherwiſe then by way of advice) the queſtion is then, Whether no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be done, which in the end amounts to little leſſe then Anarchy, the mother of conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and this of deſtruction: or that (ſeeing the officers may not) the maior part of the people ſhall corey it <hi>in foro externo?</hi> Reaſon, and the Examples of all other judicatures doe ſeeme to conclude that the moſt voyces of the Judges ought to take place.</note> truth and right, and according to God. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 72. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 58, 60.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. diſcov. p.</hi> 78, 261. <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea. <hi>p.</hi> 307.</p>
               <p>Sometimes they grant indeed all things are curried by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155017:19"/>conſent of all; but then they explain it thus, <hi>viz.</hi> That if it fall out that any leſſer number doe diſſent, then the greater indeavour to give unto, or to receive from them due ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; which if it be done then all agree in one vote. If the leſſer party diſſenting neither can give ſatisfaction to the greater, nor will receive ſatisfaction from them, but ſtill perſiſt in diſſenting, then doe the maior part (after due for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, and calling in the counſell of ſome neighbouring Churches)<note n="b" place="margin">Indeed it were much better that the whole Church, and every member thereof did conſent, but to extort and force a conſent after this manner, ſeemes not only harſh and uncharitable, but alſo fooliſh, yea, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive too: For ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the aforeſaid ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time proceed to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication or not: If it may not, then 'its vain and of no efficacie to compell conſent; it may rather occaſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. If it may, then (as ſuppoſe it be in the caſe of admiſſion of ſome member) for the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of one man (and that perhaps none of the beſt neither) 7, 10, or 20. may be loſt, and be cut off from the Church. But were it not better to let all things currantly paſſe by the moſt voyces, then thus by ſeeking to force an univerſall conſent to expoſe the Church to ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and inconveniences.</note> judicially admoniſh them; who being thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cenſure, their voyce is now extinct, and made voide. And ſo the reſt proceed to vote, which vote is now the vote of all the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> of all that have the power of voting therein. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 58, 61.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Notwithſtanding all this power aforeſaid, by them attributed to this Church, when it is yet young, of very ſmall number and without officers too. Yet doe they deny unto it (though growne never ſo numerous and well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with godly and learned officers, and withall ſtrengthened with the conſent of other Churches, and the Chriſtian Magiſtrates authoritie)<note n="c" place="margin">Yet contrary to this Article, I beleeve, themſelves take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to appoint ſome humane obſervances, or which is worſe, to impoſe them on mens conſciences for divine Ordinances.</note> all power to make any particular rules or lawes in things indifferent (conducing to the better government of her ſelfe, and more orderly, and more edifying performance of Gods worſhip, and uſe of his Ordinances) according to the generall rules of Scripture in ſuch caſes provided. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 66. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 9. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. diſcov. p.</hi> 84, 255. <hi>Rob. Apol. p.</hi> 73.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:155017:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Church memberſhip and admiſsion of more members into the Church thus constituted and erected.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. ALL men are bound, ſay they, to become<note n="d" place="margin">What if it bee (though poſſible) yet for the preſent very inconvenient, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodious, may they not delay a while? No, ſay they; yet becauſe that might ſeeme harſh and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, therfore to ingage the more, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to make the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement the more eaſie, they allow ſome to be admitted as members tranſient, for the time onely. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 20, 27. But why may not this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour be allowed to all as well as to ſome? Alſo how doth this agree with the tenour of the covenant that limits no time? and with the ſenſe of it, that (as they conceive) obligeth all the members to aske and take counſell of the Church, and not to remove without their conſent as is both before and after ſaid?</note> ſetled mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of ſuch a particular Church, as is before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; And whoſoever doth not, (if poſſibly he can) ſinneth. And whether he can or no, yet he remaines for the time without the viſible Church of Chriſt (for which they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently alleadge 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.) and in that eſtate uncapable of any<note n="e" place="margin">Yet ſometimes themſelves conſeſſe that men converted have right to the Sacraments, and Church priviledges in their ſtate, as beleevers and men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: If there were any that could adminiſter the ſame unto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> which ordinary Miniſters cannot do, ſay they, whoſe power reacheth only to church members. Theſe things do not cohere.</note> Church ordinance or priviledge, though he be not only baptized, but alſo truly converted, yea, eminent in the profeſſion of faith, and practiſe of holineſſe, even unto mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome it ſelfe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11, 30, 38. | <hi>D. ag. P. p.</hi> 4. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 6. Nay, he is accounted as one that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Church-fellowſhip, and ſo unworthy of it, yea, wicked and prophane. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 25, 26, 27, 34. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 69, 62. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11, 12, 21. | <hi>J. W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 56, 71, 85, 86.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Perſons admitted are either infants, or ſuch as are of age.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When any perſon of age is to be admitted, he is firſt to deſire and ſeeke it in this or that particular Church. And therefore to make his deſire knowne to the Church by ſome of the Elders, or members of the ſame <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | <hi>J. M.</hi> to <hi>R. M.</hi> | <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> | <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Which ſaid Elders or others doe<note n="f" place="margin">If the man be not otherwiſe wel known and approved, he is not admitted to this firſt triall, till he have lived ſome good ſpace amongſt them, that they may obſerve his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, whatſoever teſtimoniall he have.</note> firſt privately exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155017:20"/>him, touching his knowledge in the Doctrine of faith, and the truth of his converſion, as is before ſhewed. <hi>H. W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> | <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> | <hi>E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C.</hi> | <hi>J. M.</hi> to <hi>R. M. Apol. p.</hi> 3, 4.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the examiners (upon this triall) conceive him not fit to enter into Church fellowſhip, then he is there ſtayed without any further proceeding. <hi>J. M.</hi> to <hi>R. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. If they find him fit, (according to the fitneſſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned CHAP. 3.) then they propound the man and his motion to the Church, who are then deſired to inquire further of him for their better ſatisfaction. And if any of them doe or ſhall (by ſuch inquirie) know any thing juſtly to hinder his admiſſion, to declare it before he be admitted. <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S. E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. After this a day is appointed (uſually on the Sabbath) and when other publike worſhip is ended, the ſaid party is called forth, and there makes<note n="g" place="margin">If the party be a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or otherwiſe weake in or preſſion, ſome tell us, that the body of the Church meets more privately in the week day, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſatisfaction tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them. <hi>E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C.</hi> But if all the Church meet then, how is it more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate? If but ſome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how ſhall the reſt (by their tenent) ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially conſent to that which they doe not know? And for delegation or repreſentation they will by no meanes allow theſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſay their confeſſions are taken privately by the examiners, and by them only related in publike to the Church, and ſo their own publike profeſſions and declarations are ſpared, as Maſter <hi>H.</hi> to <hi>S. A.</hi> intimates. But how doth this agree with the Apoſtles rule, <hi>Doe nothing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. If it be needfull that all the Church heare une man relate his converſion, why ſhould they not heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll? And if the examiners may be truſted with examining of ſome, why not of all the reſt alſo?</note> publike Profeſſion of his Faith, and declareth the manner of his converſion; which (by ſuch as can) is done in a continued ſpeech of their own; by others (not ſo well able) in making anſwers to queſtions propounded to them cocerning the ſame. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 3, 4. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with if any of the companie be not ſatisfied, his admiſſion is ſtayed for the time, till all things be cleared, and all objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons anſwered. And then by conſent of the Church, he enters into Church-covenant with them, and ſo is admitted in the ſame manner as the reſt were at the firſt conſtitution of the Church. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | <hi>H. W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> | <hi>E. C.</hi> to <hi>R. C. J. M.</hi> to <hi>R. M.</hi> | <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. After the party is ſo admitted, the Miniſter or ſome one or more of the members of that Church, in name of the reſt, do give him the right hand of fellowſhip; and do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155017:20"/>repromiſe to performe all Church duties to him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſame covenant, as unto the reſt of her members, <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Thus for admiſſion of perſons of age. Now for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants they account them in the ſame eſtate with their next parents: For if either of their next naturall parents be now, or (being deceaſed) died a member of ſome ſuch particular ſocietie, as aforeſaid, then are their children alſo accounted members, and ſo baptized, if they were not baptized before?<note n="h" place="margin">Cold comfort to Chriſtian parents (not of their way) and cold charitie to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</note> But if neither of them have been, or having been formerly, if at the preſent (being alive) neither of them be a member; then their infants (as themſelves) are accounted to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the viſible Church. In the ſame eſtate with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Turkes and Heathens, Aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, and ſo uncapable of Baptiſme, or any other Church priviledge whatſoever: yea, though the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father be a member or (perhaps) a Miniſter of that Church; or though one or more of the next parents being no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be eminently and famouſly Godly, and will undertake to educate their children in the true faith and Feare of God; And neither wilfully, nor negligently omit to joyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſuch a Church, but abſtaine only out of want of ſic opportunitie to doe it, or out of tenderneſſe of Conſcience, as ſcrupling ſome things in their way, yet for all this, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ſhall not be admitted to Baptiſme; as not being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but without the Church. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>M. Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> 61, 62, 63, &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 29.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of their diſmiſsing of members from one Church to another, or otherwiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. NO perſon once thus admitted (as aforeſaid) into any of their Churches, ought to remove thence without the conſent of the ſaid Church firſt ſought and obtained. For if lie doe, they hold that he breaks covenant with God and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155017:21"/>the Church, and like <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> lies againſt the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 73. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 39. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>E.B. p.</hi> 6. Inaſmuch as they conceive their convenant bindes them not to depart without conſent. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore when any would remove, they require that he firſt give notice thereof to the<note n="i" place="margin">Why muſt he needs conſult with this ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then any other? perhaps this may be more partiald then any other, becauſe concerned more. No man ſo fit to be judge in his own cauſe. But if with this Church, why with the whole Church? why not rather with ſome few of the more ſecret and diſcreer perſons, that know both how to give counſell, and to keep counſell? What if his reaſons be ſecret, and he cannot diſcoyer them but to his ſhame, loſſe or danger?</note> Church, wherewith he is in covenant, and lay before them (how many ſoever they be) in a publike meeting, both his reaſons for which he deſires to remove, and alſo to what other Church he would remove, and conſult with them about both. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 74. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If upon examination, they approve both of his reaſons why, and of the place whither he would goe, then they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and giving him letters of diſmiſſion and recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to that other Church, they ſend him away with their prayers and bleſſing. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If contrarily they approve not, either the one or the other, they diſſwade him from his purpoſe, if they prevaile nor, they will not hold him by violence, (for that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not,) yet they will neither give their<note n="k" place="margin">If this be ſo, as the Diſciples ſaid of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, It is not good to touch this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: A man may ſoon enter into this bond, but be cannot ſo ſoon get free again. Theſe are hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: He muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all to a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude (many of which are no wiſer then they ſhould be) who are to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s judge in their own cauſe: and who can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure him of their judicious and unpartiall dealing? It may be (though his reaſons be never ſo ſufficient yet) they will not conſent to his departure; And if he depart without conſent, he goes not only not commended, but tacitely accuſed, ſlandered: not only not bleſt, but virtually caſt out and curſt; and to make up his miſerie, (if all Courches were of their way,) for ever made uncapable of admiſſion into any other Church; and ſo neceſſitated to live (be and his) all their dayes as an heathen and publican without the pale of the Church. There being (as it ſeemes) a tacite agreement amongſt them to receive no members from one Church to another, unleſſe they bring with them letters of diſmiſſion and recommendation. Yea, a man that is once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into this way, is ſo rivetted in it, that he can hardly ever get out of it; but in a ſort, is neceſſitated to continue therein, though perhaps againſt his conſcience. Seeing depart he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (with leave) unleſſe they approve of the Church to which he would goe, as well as of the reaſons why. Now they will not approve of any Church that differs from themſelves in Church conſtitution, diſcipline and government. Therefore he muſt either continue where he is, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to ſome other Church of the ſame way, or live out of Church eſtate like an heathen, as aforeſaid. The beſt of all which choiſes may prove bad enough. This ſo ſtrict and hard tying of men together (unleſſe it can be proved to be an ordinance of God) muſt needs be an into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable burden, preſſing and pinching men not only in their eſtates, names and comforts, but alſo in their conſciences too. Sometimes cauſing ſharpe conteſts and contentions with, yea, perhaps deadly hatred of ſuch with whom they arc ſo forced to continue in ſocietie againſt their minds, or wils, at leaſt. And ſometimes violent rents and ruptures, when they are feigne to breake away from them by violence, by whom with good leave they cannot be diſmiſt. When I conſider theſe ſtrict tyings of people to their owne members and officers, I cannot but pitie the good people of this Kingdome, eſpecially of this Citie, if the <hi>New England</hi> Diſcipline and Government ſhould take place, (as many of them do deſire.) For how will they indure to be ſo tyed, who have ſo long time accuſtomed to keep with no ſocietie, but to picke and chooſe, now one and then another, every Sabbath almoſt a new Miniſterie and a new Church; yea, tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hold it as a Maxime, That they will be bound to none; That they may lawfully goe where they like beſt, and where they can profit moſt, &amp;c</note> conſent, nor give him their letters of recommendation (though he were otherwiſe never ſo well deſerving) nor ſend him away with their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, as otherwiſe they would. <hi>Ibid.</hi> Yea, he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part little better then an excommunicate, as a Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaker with God and man, and as one that is wiſe in his own conceit, and refuſeth to hearken to counſell. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:155017:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Church-Communion in generall, wherein it conſists, to whom it doth belong, of corruptions in it, and ſeparation from it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey ſolicitouſly diſtinguiſh betweene Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and Chriſtian or religious communion. This latter they hold generally with all whom they conceive to be true Chriſtians, without reference to their Church eſtate, and whether they be in Church eſtate or no: therefore they will conferre, pray with them, &amp;c.<note n="l" place="margin">If by Church were to be meant only ſuch a particular body as is before by them defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the diſtinction might the rather paſſe. But foraſmuch as the word Church in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſometimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it ſelfe to all, or any beleevers on the face of the earth, without reſpect had to any ſuch congregationall union, therefore Church communion will and may extend it ſelfe to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with viſible beleevers in all religious duties whatſoever. For as there is a perſecution of the Church, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. Prayers of the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.5. and a communion of Saints with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch a reſpect, ſo a communion of the Church in all religious duties, without ſuch a reſpect.</note> But the former they hold onely with ſuch as they acknowledge to be true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155017:22"/>and with their Church-members. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62, 63. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 28, 34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robinſ.</hi> hath a diſtinction not much unlike, of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and publike communion, that he allowes with all Chriſtians, this only with Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; concerning which ſee his whole treatiſe of publike and private communion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They call that Church communion which is only in ſuch duties, priviledges and ordinances as are proper to ſuch a particular ſocietie, and belong to none other, as 1. Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of members into their ſocietie. 2. Mutuall watchfulneſſe of each member over other. 3. Admonition in way to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. 4. Excommunication. 5. Re-acception into ſocietie again upon repentance. 6. Adminiſtration, and receiving of the ſeales. 7. Vocation of Miniſters and all other officers, and depoſing of them again. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 63. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 7. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 27-29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for<note n="m" place="margin">Here we may ſee how much and how long we have been miſtaken: For when our brethren of that way doe ſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (perhaps fixedly) preach and pray with us not only privately in houſes, but in our publike aſſemblies alſo, we (fooles) thinke all this while, they hold Church communion with us, and do thereby actually own our Miniſterie and Church eſtate as true. But, alas, there is no ſuch matter. It is but Chriſtian communion at the beſt, neither doe they at all preach unto us, or pray with us, as Miniſters <hi>ex officio,</hi> much leſſe as our Miniſters; No they will not confeſſe themſelves to be ſo much as members of our Churches: but <hi>ex deno,</hi> only as men well giſted, and ſo able to edifie the church by their gifts, as meere private men, <hi>ex com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni officio charitatis,</hi> as any man elſe may doe that hath a gift to ſpeake to the churches edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. Nay, what doe they more to us in publike then they would do to ſo many Turks or Indians, to whom they would preach, and with and for whom they would pray (I beleeve) as well as they do unto and with, and for us. If they judged any Church communion to conſiſt in any of theſe things they could (following their own principles) no more joyn with us in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and prayer, then now they doe in Sacraments. The like is to be thought of their hearing of our Miniſters alſo.</note> preaching, reading and hearing the word, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, praying, ſinging of Pſalmes, bleſſing the people, &amp;c. though performed by Church officers and members onely, and in the Church Aſſembly onely, yet in theſe, they hold, there is no Church communion at all. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 7, 28. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 26, 34. <hi>Rob. justif. p.</hi> 192, 195.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Theſe things, ſay they, doe not onely belong to Church Communion, but to the Communion of this<note n="n" place="margin">How doth this agree with that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes after of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and receiving of Sacraments in other Churches by vertue of the communion of churches.</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:155017:22"/>particular Church onely, of which one is ſtated a member; and therefore are to be performed onely to the members thereof, and not to the members of other Churches, much leſſe to any ſuch as are not at all in Church eſtate. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Eſpecially Sacraments are to be adminiſtred (as onely by Miniſters of the ſame Churches as after ſo) onely to Church<note n="o" place="margin">How is it then that they acknowledge <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 63, 64. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 6, 7, 21, 40. that ſcattied members of Chriſt may partake of the Sacraments as members of the Catholique Church. Alſo that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments do rightfully belong to all viſible beleevers and their ſced, as ſuch, if ſo be there were any Miniſters now that might lawfully adminiſter the ſame unto them, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as were the Apoſſles and Evangeliſts. And that the reaſon why they cannot now actually partake therein, is becauſe now ordinary Miniſters power extends not beyond the bounds of their own church. Whence I inferre, 1. that then church-memberſhip is not neceſſarie to participation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, of it ſelfe, but by accident only. 2. that beleevers are not uncapable of Sacraments (by their own tenent) through any defect in themſelves but in the miniſterie, (that I ſay not, in God) they indeed are capable of them, but God hath provided no miniſterie to adminiſter the ſame to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I mean, to ſcattred Saints. 3. That participation of Sacraments is no part of church communion, ſince of right it belongs as well to all viſible beleevers, as ſuch, though they be no church members at all. 4. That Baptiſme is not given only to a Church body. 5. That it was not intended as a ſeale of the Church-covenant: All which are contrary to their tenents.</note> members, and<note n="p" place="margin">Here alſo they ſeeme as before not conſtant to themſelves, who after tell us that by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Churches the Miniſter of one Church may adminiſter the Sacraments to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of another Church: why not then to ſuch as are members of no Church alſo (being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers) ſeeing the A poſtles did ſo: and ſeeing ordinary Miniſters have as much power over ſuch as are no members, as over the members of another Church, both being without the Church to them.</note> members of the ſame Church. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 62, 63, 64, 66, 70. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11, 12, 37. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 29, 30, 39, 40, 41. <hi>Cott. cat. p.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. They hold that if any ſinne be committed by any in the Church, for want of watchfulneſſe, and admonition in others, all the body is defiled therewith, and made liable to a common judgement, as was all Iſrael by <hi>Achans</hi> ſinne. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q.p.</hi> 50. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.p.</hi> 75. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 7. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That a man that is <hi>ſui juris,</hi> may not lawfully ſtand member of ſuch a Church, in which he cannot obſerve and enjoy all Gods ordinances, nor where any<note n="q" place="margin">Who then may ſtand members of their Churches? or will they ſay that there are no corruptions amongſt them ſuffered? doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may be judges, (not themſelves who are parties) they are faulty one way, as well as others are another way. It may be alſo as hard to reduce as others are.</note> corruption in Gods worſhip, or other ſinne is ſuffered unreformed, but if
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155017:23"/>he be joyned to it, he muſt ſeparate from it, elſe he is defiled therewith. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 32, 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 15, 16, 197, 200, 201. <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea, <hi>p.</hi> 245. <hi>Barr. diſcov. p.</hi> 26, 29, 34, 38.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Eſpecially where any ſet Leitourgy, or<note n="r" place="margin">Yet themſelves allow ſet formes of Pſalmes to be ſang as Prayers and Praifes to God, and of benedictions or bleſſing the people, of church covenan (as before) ſome of them alſo ſet formes of catechiſing, and confeſſions of Faith, as <hi>H. P.</hi> | <hi>I C.</hi> his Catechiſme of the Church. So <hi>Robinſons</hi> cat. of Diſcipline, added to the end of <hi>Perkins</hi> cat. Why then not a ſet forme of Prayer too? whereas they diſlike ſet formes becauſe impoſed: I cannot ſee how bare impoſition by lawfull authoritie of that which is lawfull (ſo far onely as it is lawfull) ſhould make it unlawfull; I ſhould rather thinke it ſhould make it neceſſarie: And whereas they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate that our ſet formes have been ſo impoſed as leave no libertie of adding, altering or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any thing away: I anſwer, we have no ſuch impoſition among us, ſeeing all experience hath ſhewed that any man might lawfully adde, what he would, though by the law, he might not, perhaps, take away or alter ought: But ſuppoſing the worſt that our ſet formes were ſo rigidly impoſed by law, that no man might adde to, or alter, or take away ought, yet if Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters did both adde to what they thought defective, and alter what was offenſive, and leave out what they judged unlawfull; I ſee no reaſon why the fault of the impoſers ſhould be imputed to ſuch as obeyed their impoſition no further then it was faultleſſe.</note> ſet forme of prayer is impoſed to be uſed. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 52, 59, 60, 61. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>M.</hi> to <hi>J.M. Cott. cat. p.</hi> 5, 6. | <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>E.B.p.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea, <hi>p.</hi> 245, 285. <hi>Brown.</hi> confeſſ. art. 45. <hi>Cannes</hi> neceſſ. of ſeparation, p. 110. <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 344.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And where<note n="ſ" place="margin">If they will walke cloſe to their owne principles; they muſt grant that not onely open and groſſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked defile the worſhip of God to all the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, but alſo unregenerate perſons, and all that give not good evidence of their converſion, yea, even ſecret ſinness alſo (ſuch as <hi>Achan</hi> was) though perhaps they have the truth of grace, if they be admitted. Of which ſee before Art. 6. But then who ſhall eſcape free? or with what ſocietie can a man joyne to be aſſured not to be defiled?</note> bad men are ſuffred to come to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments with the good, becauſe thereby both the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all that partake in them are defiled. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 37. <hi>J. D.</hi> to <hi>L.H.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. diſcov.</hi> p. 34. <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 15, 197, 201, 204.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:155017:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the Communion of Churches one with another, and of ſeparation from corrupt Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey grant that ſeverall Churches have a<note n="t" place="margin">If there be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Churches, then an union, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many therefore may be rightly called one. And if an union of many Churches without Covenant, why not alſo of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny members in the ſame Church without covenant.</note> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt themſelves, whereby they do and may<note n="u" place="margin">How can this ſtand with their doctrine of the covenant before, which tyeth the members to church duties only to their own Church? and that Sacraments belong onely to the members of their owne Church: and with their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine following that Miniſters are Miniſters only to their own people, and cannot doe a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall act to any but ſuch as by calling them, have given them power over them, which ſome of themſelves perceiving, rather then part with this latter (which they hugge as a precious truth) are content to queſtion the former of the communion of Churches, as <hi>S. E.</hi>
                  </note> mutually partake each with other in ſome Church-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,<note n="*" place="margin">If this may be done in Sacraments (by vertue of Church communion) why not in Ordination and Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication alſo?</note> as Sacraments. And that this Communion is both between the Miniſters and members of the ſame. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 62, 78. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 29. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 2, 13. | <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>E.B.</hi> p. 11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By vertue of this Church communion, they ſay; one Church by letters of recommendation may give power to another Church over any of her members for Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the<note n="x" place="margin">This Divinitie is ſtrange to me: Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hold the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters power is not his own, but concredited to him by the church, ſo that he is but a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie himſelf, <hi>&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a non poteſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putare.</hi> How then ſhould he derive his authoritie to another, and convey his power over to him, as his deputie, who himſelfe is but the Churches deputie?</note> Miniſters of one Church may convey pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the Miniſters of another Church for Adminiſtration of the Sacraments to any of their members. <hi>Cott. cat.</hi> p. 7. <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 2, 14, 26, 40. | <hi>J.W.</hi> to <hi>T.S.</hi> Hence the infants of ſome of <hi>Windſor</hi> Church in <hi>N.E.</hi> have been baptized by the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> there. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But without ſuch letters of recommendations, and formall granting over of ſuch power, from one Church and Miniſter to another, it were<note n="y" place="margin">They are very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of loſing any of their members, and of having them but to communicate for a time with any other churches but their own: but they make no bomes of getting all the members they can from cur Miniſters and Churches, belike we have neither true Miniſters nor Churches, and therefore they may doe with us what they liſt.</note> unlawfull in any caſe to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155017:24"/>any Church ordinance to any Church or members but their owne, or to admit them to any Church communion upon any pretence whatſoever. <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 14, 26, 40.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Though they hold it lawfull by this Communion of Churches for one Church to admit the members of another unto fellowſhip of Church ordinances and priviledges; yet not of every Church. But they thinke themſelves bound to know the Church well (whoſe members they ſo admit, as well as the members themſelves) whether it bee a true Church or a falſe, a pure Church, or a corrupt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 10 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And that if they ſhould admit any members of a falſe Church, they ſhould offend in ſo holding communion with a falſe Church; yea, if they ſhould admit any members of a corrupt Church, they ſhould be defiled by ſuch communion; unleſſe they did firſt proteſt againſt their corruptions. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 29. | <hi>J.C.</hi> printed letter, p. 12. yet they hold no ſuch<note n="z" place="margin">What ground for this diſtinction, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement by Church communion, and no defilement by religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous communion?</note> defilement by admitting them unto religious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, though their Church were not only impure, but ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They are very ſtraight-laced in denying communion to the members of other Churches that are not<note n="a" place="margin">This is one cauſe and the chief why our moſt godly <hi>Engliſh</hi> going over thither are yet rejected from all Church communion there: Not becauſe of any perſonall defect, but becauſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted corrupt eſtate of our Churches, whereof they ſtand, or lately did ſtand as members.</note> conſtira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and governed in the ſame manner with their own which onely they conceive to be conſtituted and governed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rule of Chriſt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 82, 83, 84. yea, if a companie of approved godly people ſhould ſit downe neer them (where their power reacheth) differing from them onely in ſome points of Church-Government, ſome of them tell us, that not only they ſhould not be<note n="b" place="margin">If upon ſuch ſmaller differences they be ſo ſevere, how much more would they be in greater; Some of their pactie here plead hard to be indulged in ſeſſer differences, yet what thoſe are we may not know, or whether they he leſſer or greater tolerable in a Church or not, and if they be not hearkned unto, they are apt to cry out, Perſecution, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: yet when others deſire the like favour of them, they tell us there is no favour to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected if we perſiſt to breake any Rule of Chriſt, their meaning is, if we follow them not cloſe in their wayes. So partiall and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfiſh are ſome men, that they thinke all ſeveritie to others too little, to themſelves too much.</note> owned as a ſiſter Church, but ſhould alſo be in danger of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155017:24"/>ſevere puniſhment by the civill Magiſtrate. <hi>H.W.</hi> to <hi>P.H. What they hold of our Engliſh Churches and Miniſters ſee in the Poſtſcript.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Excommunication and Re-acception into Church-fellowſhip again upon repentance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>N. I find little difference herein betweene them and others of the reformed Religion, more then what is above touched, ſave that</p>
               <p n="1">1. I Heare ſome of them have preſt that not only the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, but alſo the<note n="f" place="margin">And no marvell For if none muſt be of the Church but reall Saints, ſuch as have truth of grace, which they cannot have that do not in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grow in grace, therfore it muſt needs follow that ſuch ſhould be caſt out. And by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cut with all that doe not convincingly ſhew all ſuch evidences of grace, as Divines (from Scripture) do l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y down as demonſtrations of grace in men. But if we cloſely hold to this way of triall of the members of true viſible Churches, we may well make Churches (as the Browniſts) conſiſting of 2. or 3. or perhaps (as our <hi>N.E.</hi> brethren) of 7, 8, or <hi>c.</hi> members, but we ſhall rarely (if ever) meet with ſuch numerous Churches as the Scriptures hold forth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as all Churches ought to be, as neare as may be.</note> non-proficients, that grow not in grace under the meanes, might be excommunicated; Which was the ground (as ſome of them report) of a groundleſſe courſe ſet on foot amongſt them at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>N. Engl. That the people met together privately at certain times, weekly or fortnightly, each one to hold forth unto the reſt the work of God upon his or her ſoul, from their firſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion unto that preſent day, that ſo their Pastour might know how they grew in grace.</hi> A.W. <hi>to</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> B.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of Church officers, their office, manner of calling, their power, maintainance, and the diſ-officing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of them again.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. WHen a Church by admiſſion of more members, is now grown to a competent number (which oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155017:25"/>proves ſome<note n="g" place="margin">No wonder it is long firſt, what for want of ſuch choice members as they ſeek, and what for want of choice Miniſters: for they tell us to our comfort that many that were counted good Miniſters in old <hi>Eng.</hi> are there laid aſide, becauſe the Churches there doe aime at men of ſpeciall abilities.</note> yeares firſt) then they addreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the calling of ſome to the Miniſtery, and other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Church. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If any of their own members be fit for the ſervice, they make choice of them. If not, they procure elſewhere. Yet ſo that none is choſen to be an officer in any Church, till he be firſt formally admitted<note n="h" place="margin">Church memberſhip is the ſalt that ſealons all things. 'Its ſtrange that his memberſhip in the Church whence he laſt came (by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Churches) can ſtand him in no ſtead.</note> member of the ſame Church, in the ſame manner every way, as others have beene. <hi>H.W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſeverall Churches with them, (how ſmall ſoever, and though as yet without any officers) doe challenge to themſelves both power and execution of all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do belong to the calling and creating of their own offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, as, 1. To<note n="i" place="margin">What abilities moſt good men have in judging of Miniſters, as reaſon ſo their own experience will tell them, when as (if I be rightly informed) all the members of the Church of <hi>Boſton</hi> (ſome few excepted) did ſtrongly ſtickle to have had M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wheel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> (that famous Familiſt) joyned as co teacher with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>C.</hi> in that Church. Alſo ſee <hi>Apol. Narr. p.</hi> 24.</note> examine and try their abilities and fitneſſe. 2. To elect them. 3. To inſtruct them in their office, at their ordination. 4. To ordaine them with impoſition of hands, prayers, and charges given them. And in ſumme, to give them all the power of their office in that Church in the name of Chriſt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 40, 41, 42, 68, 71. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov.</hi> p. 23. | <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 70, 77. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>W.R.</hi> | <hi>H.W.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 300, 303. <hi>Cannes</hi> Neceſs. of ſepar. p. 29. <hi>Barr. refut. of Giff.</hi> p. 130. <hi>A light for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ign.</hi> p. 7. <hi>Rob. Apology.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Whereby it is come to paſſe, that every of their firſt Miniſters (at leaſt) in every of their Churches, is ordained by one or more<note n="k" place="margin">Have not wee as much cauſe to doubt of the truth of their miniſterie, as they of ours, they being made by meere private men (<hi>i.e.</hi>) not in any office, ours by Presbyters at leaſt, and therein according to the Apoſtles rule, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. ſeeing the Biſhops themſelves were Presbyters, with whom were other Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ever joyned in Ordination of any: Beſides, the choice and approbation of many of us by our people alſo: whether they or we come neerer to the Rule, let the Reader judge.</note> private men, appointed by the reſt, in their names to pray over them, impoſe hands upon them, inſtruct, charge them, and give them authoritie there to miniſter:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155017:25"/>The act being the act of the whole Church, but for order, and eaſe ſake, the formalitie is committed to one or two, in name of the reſt:<note n="l" place="margin">The Levites electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was from God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and their Ordination by the Prieſt by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, <hi>Numb.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.11, 13, 14. The peoples laying on of their hands in this work was not authoritative, that were needleſſe, when God had authoriſed them both immediately by himſelfe and mediately by the Prieſt before, if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, that they ſhould interpoſe their authoritie, when God himſelfe had eſtabliſhed them by his. But either it was obedientiall only, to declare their approbation of Gods choice and Ordination, and then it is nothing to our brethrens authoritative impoſition of the peoples hands. Or rather (as I conceive) for the ſame end for which they were commanded to lay hands on the head of the ſacrifice to be oftred (as verſ. 12.) <hi>viz.</hi> to ſigniſie that they, <hi>i.e.</hi> their firſt born by right were all the Lords, and did owe to be, but that God of his goodneſſe was now pleaſed to accept of the Levites for them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.</note> As the Iſraelites laid hands on the Levites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 8.10. | <hi>J.M.</hi> to <hi>R.M.</hi> | <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 68, 69, 70. <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>E.B.</hi> p. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif. p.</hi> 328, 331, 338.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They hold that the peoples<note n="m" place="margin">By this reaſon (me thinks) all that are elected by the people to a conſtant exerciſe to a conſtant exerciſe of the chiefe dutie of the Paſtours office (which is prenching of the Word) and do alſo by compact receive the tithes and wages due by law to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour, ſhould be the Paſtours of the places where by the peoples choice they doe ſo preach, and by conſequent many of our brethren of that way, here in <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be Paſtours of many of our Pariſh Churches. But doe they count themſelves ſo? or do they carry themſelves ſo?</note> Election is not onely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall unto, but alſo the whole ſubſtance of the calling of the Miniſter, or other officer. But as for Ordination with impoſition of hands of the Presbyterie, or other ſigne, they hold it not eſſentiall at all, but a meere formalitie, or ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the calling; the preſence whereof addeth nothing to the ſubſtance of the calling, and the abſence thereof takes nothing from it. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 67, 68, 69. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 23. | <hi>R.M.</hi> to <hi>E.B.</hi> p. 10. <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 308, 332, 333, 334, 335. <hi>Rob. Apol.</hi> p. <hi>Per electionem jus miniſterii Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris confertur, &amp;c. Barr. refut. of Giff.</hi> p. 219, 130.</p>
               <p n="6">6. After the firſt officers are thus made by the Church, the formalitie of ordaining the reſt, is ordinarily committed to ſuch<note n="n" place="margin">So that if they have but one Paſtour or Teacher he alone laies hand on the next offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to be ordained: But S<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Pauls</hi> rule for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination is, that it ſhould bee done by the hands of the Presbyterie, not of one Imgle Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, much leſſe of one private man.</note> officers as are alreadie called and ordained, not as having any more power (by vertue of their office) to doe it, then before; for the power is the Churches, and belongs equally to every member, as a member; but as being the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155017:26"/>Churches publike ſervants, to doe it for them, and in threi name and ſtead. See the quotations cited before <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 321, 323, 327.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the ſorts or kinds of their officers, they agree with others of the beſt reformed Churches.<note n="o" place="margin">I will not impute to the generall that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinion (but too publikely here) by ſome of them vented: that the Paſtor is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to feed the people with wholeſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders onely to viſit them, and ſee to their manners.</note> Onely whereas in opinion and tenent they preciſely diſtinguiſh between the Paſtors and Teachers office, yet in practiſe they uſually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them: both Paſtour and Teacher equally teaching and equally applying both the Word and Seales without any difference. And either of them uſually ſupplying the place of both in divers of their Churches, which are not furniſhed with both. See <hi>J. C.</hi> his Sermons on <hi>Revel.</hi> and other texts, for proof of this: Beſides what we have by others report.</p>
               <p n="8">8. They hold the officers ſo called and made by this Church, are officers onely in and unto this particular Church, that hath ſo called them. And bound onely to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to that, and the members thereof, and to none other. So that the Paſtors and Teachers thereof may lawfully doe no<note n="p" place="margin">Yet their Miniſters frequently adminiſter the Sacraments to the members of other Churches then their own: They will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that is done by vertue of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Churches. I reply, But this latter rule quite overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the former and all the reaſons they bring for it; which ſome perceiving, queſtion this rule of communion of Churches, others to maintain the former have invented a power in every particular Church and Miniſter to transfer their own power over to another Church and Miniſter <hi>pro tempore,</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Seales, (yea, and cenſures too) to any of their members, ſo that tranſlation be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally done, as before <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. If there can be no act valid where there is no power. Whether miniſteriall acts done by a miniſter in and unto another Church be not null and voide: which if they be, then have we millions of perſons of age unbaptized to this very day.</note> miniſteriall act whatſoever in or unto any other Church or the members thereof, then their own. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 11, 15, 70. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 64, 67, 70, 76, 78. <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 14, 26, 29, 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. justif.</hi> p. 317, 318, 335.</p>
               <p n="9">9. They grant indeed that Miniſters may preach unto, and pray with other Churches and their members, becauſe theſe are properly no miniſteriall acts. Onely the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the<note n="q" place="margin">Preaching and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing were wont to be joyned together, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. And the Word and Prayer to be counted chiefe imployments of the Miniſters, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. yea, Preaching rather then Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. But it is the nature of popular government to incroach upon all or moſt of the rights of the miniſterie, which muſt either have nothing to doe, or but what the people will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and lend them their power for to do. Alas poore Miniſters, it ſeemes it is their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinie ever to be ſervants (if good) yea ſlaves and foot-ſtools. Hitherto they have been troden under foot by the Prelates, and now they muſt be by their people!</note> Sacraments (with them) are properly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155017:26"/>and therefore belong onely to the Miniſters. All other acts are common to other members, either by vertue of their gifts, and <hi>ex communi officio charitatis,</hi> or by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Keyes, which they have received in common with that Church of which they are members, or by a temporarie deputation from the ſame. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 78.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 195.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They hold that a Miniſters calling lives and dyes with his union unto and diſuniting from that particular Church wherein and whereby he was ſo called, as before. So that if a Miniſter lawfully choſen and ordained in one place, ſhall remove (upon never ſo juſt and neceſſary grounds) to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation: He is thereby diveſted of his former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, and now become as a meere private man again, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and untill he ſhall be called and ſo created again by the ſame or ſome other Congregation. In which caſe he is not only to be elected anew, but alſo to be ordained anew, by the impoſition of the hands (perhaps of ſome meere private man or men) as if he had never been ordained before. And ſo <hi>toties quoties. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 69, 70. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 67, 77. <hi>J. W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>quest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 317.</p>
               <p n="11">11. They hold the Miniſters are but the Churches ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, her mouth by whom ſhe ſpeakes, and hands whereby ſhe acts. And therefore though they meet together to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of matters for the good of the Churches, or to prepare matters for the Churches hearing; yet in point of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they can<note n="r" place="margin">Yet M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>P.</hi> tels us that the Miniſters have there agreed amongſt themſelves that none of them ſhall preach any doctrine that is not commonly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved amongſt them, till he have firſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated it with the teſt of the Miniſters: And what's this but in effect a compound Presbyterie ruling without peoples votes, and alſo a Canon made by common conſent and impoſed: both contrary to their own principles.</note> decree, act, or execute<note n="ſ" place="margin">They call them rulers, and tell us they have great power of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſhew us nothing that they may doe (except Adminiſtration of Sacraments) which others may not as lawfully doe as they: unleſſe they will ſay (as <hi>Rob juſtif. p.</hi> 116.) that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters rule conſiſts in ſerving the Church, and the people obey their Miniſters in uſing their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: which is moſt abſurd in reaſon and contradictious to it ſelf.</note> nothing but what the Church doth dictate and direct: <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 57.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. Apol.</hi> p. 49. Sions royall Prerog. <hi>p.</hi> 26, 20.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:155017:27"/>
               <p n="12">12. Miniſters (they hold) are onely Miniſters of Churches already gathered, which are all ſuppoſed to be already reall Saints, effectually called. So that the end and work of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Miniſters and their Miniſterie, is onely the confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and building up of men already converted and inchurch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Nor are they bound by vertue of their office to attend unto the work of<note n="t" place="margin">Thus the Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinners which is the crowne of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Calling, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> is pulled off their heads, and put on the head of every gifted bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and why not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter too? ſince ſuch may poſſibly convert alſo: and if they may convert, belike they may conſirme as well, and ſo they may take all; For what then hath the Miniſter left him to doe by office? But if this were ſo it would follow, 1. That a Miniſter of a Church need not by office preach ſome Doctrines, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrines of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of Chriſt, at leaſt not in ſome manner of teaching them: whence it is that ſpire have held that the Miniſter is to apply himſelfe in all his Sermons to the members, and not to them that are without: the reſt of the members are to doe that in their prophecying. <hi>N. P.</hi> 2. That Miniſters being fixed to particular charges, to which they ovve themſelves, and all that they can poſſibly doe, are thereby bound out from labouring in the worke of converſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at all: it being both without the compaſſe of their calling (by this doctrine) and beyond the poſſibilitie of their povver too, 3. And therefore that either men unconverted muſt ſo continue, and periſh in their ſins, for want of ſome body to ſeek and bring them home, Or elſe men gifted, that are no Miniſters (which I feare upon account will prove but few) muſt leave their callings, and give themſelves to the preaching of the word and Prayer, which both were diligently practiſed by the Apoſtles (as Miniſters) and with ſtrict charge impoſed upon all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to practiſe (as belonging to their office) to the end of the world. Again, it this be ſo, how is it that ſome of our brethren of that way, are far more buſie in ſeeking our cunverſion here (not ſo much to grace, as to their Church covenant) then to build up their own Churches, with which they are in covenant already at home?</note> converting ſouls, any more then other gifted brethren are, who owe it by the office of common charitie. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 80, 82.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 308, 11, 47.</p>
               <p>whence it muſt needs follow that either none are converted in their Churches by their miniſterie, or elſe if any be, that fals out only accidentally, not as the direct end of their office, and Gods Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="13">13. They acknowledge a moſt<note n="u" place="margin">A right tenent, if rightly underſtood &amp; limitted: But how comes it then that ſome of them that have charges, as Paſtours, in other Kingdomes far off, yet take and hold places of ſetled miniſteriall imployment here?</note> ſtrict tye between the Miniſter and his people, and that the one hath ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie in the other. <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 11, 24. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B.</hi> p. 11.</p>
               <p n="14">14. They conceive it unwarrantable that Miniſters ſhould have ſet and certain ſtipends or wages, much leſſe that they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:155017:27"/>ſhould live upon tithes: But rather upon the peoples<note n="*" place="margin">Let the unpartiall Reader (now laying all ends together) judge whether the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, according to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r rules, be not the unhappieſt ſervants under Heaven; For 1. they muſt ſerve ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maſters, perhaps many hundred. 2. doe great worke. 3. Yet nothing (in effect) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to them, but as other ſervants of the Church. 4. Yet may neither know the certain bounds of their obedience: 5. Nor indent for certain wages: 6. Nor change their maſter or miſtreſle if they doe not like, they may poſſibly be expulſt, at the Churches pleaſure, but never can depart at their own: But if this be ſo, how comes it to paſſe that ſome of them amongſt us, doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive, but ſtrictly require ſo much ſet ſtipend for ſuch a Lecture, and ſo much more for ſuch another, or elſe they will not preach; but alſo can be content to take the glebe, tithes and other profits of ſequeſtred Parſonages and Vicaridges amongſt us, as well as others. But in ſome ſort, I marvell not at it, if that be true (which we are credibly informed) that ſome of our brethren of the miniſterie there have not long ſince complained that their Prophets did now prophecie in ſacke for want of maintainance. <hi>M. B.</hi> to <hi>S. A.</hi> and others of them out of their love have warned us of the like danger, if tithes (amongſt us) ſhould goe downe. Mr. <hi>W.</hi> to Mr. <hi>M.</hi> And therefore no marvell if our brethren that have been bitten with the peoples cold contributions there, be content to forſake that rule, and to covenant for wages, as we doe here.</note> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary contribution, weekly caſt into the common treaſurie, according to their weekly gaines: Out of which the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons are to diſtribute both unto the officers and poore, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which is brought in, and as they conceive to be fit and needfull for every one. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> to <hi>S. A.</hi> | <hi>J. W.</hi> to <hi>T. S.</hi> | <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 77. <hi>Cott. cat.</hi> p. 7, 8. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B.</hi> p. 7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. justif.</hi> p. 214, 353. <hi>Barr. Diſcov.</hi> p. 53, 61, 62. <hi>Brow. Confeſſ. art.</hi> 20, 45.</p>
               <p n="15">15. As this Church hath power to make her own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſo alſo to<note n="x" place="margin">Which power (we heare) alſo they have uſed upon very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grounds, as in M. <hi>W.</hi> | <hi>S. B.</hi> | <hi>R. S.</hi> their caſes.</note> queſtion, cenſure, unmake and depoſe them; and by reaſſuming their power, to reduce them into the ſtate of meere private men again. And this alſo they claime pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe (as well as the other) without any authoritative concurrence of any others whomſoever; whoſe counſell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may, and perhaps will crave and uſe, yet that is done freely without any authoritative obligation <hi>in foro ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 41. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ.</hi> p. 77. | <hi>J. C.</hi> printed letter, p. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 111, 176, 177. Sions royall Prerog. <hi>p.</hi> 26. | <hi>Seper. Conf. art.</hi> 23. <hi>Cann.</hi> neceſſ. of ſe. par. <hi>p.</hi> 155.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:155017:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of thoſe whom they call Prophets, and of prophecying, or private mens preaching.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey hold it lawfull for meere private perſons (<hi>i.e.</hi> ſuch as neither are in office, nor are ever likely to be) to exerciſe their gifts in and before the whole Congregation, in<note n="y" place="margin">Some ſay without any Moderator, at pleaſure, whereby ſtrange things have been vented, &amp; Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſometimes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly abuſed. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>W.</hi>
                  </note> preaching, <hi>i. e.</hi> in expounding and applying the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the ſeverall uſes of the auditors, by inſtruction, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, reprehenſion, with all authoritie; yea, that this is an ordinary and perpetuall ordinance in the Church grounded upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. | <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 78. <hi>Cott. cat.</hi> p. 6. | <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B.</hi> p. 7. There is a book printed, called, A Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Plimmouth</hi> in <hi>N. E.</hi> which (as I am certified) was made there by a Comber of wooll.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. justif. p.</hi> 183. <hi>Johnſ. Inq.</hi> p. 7. A light for the ignor. <hi>p.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>Some of them (indeed) tell us that its ſeldome uſed, <hi>viz.</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where the Church is<note n="z" place="margin">But ſuch occaſions are not rare with them, who oft for a long time want Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, at leaſt a full ſupply. Alſo ſome of them have their farmes, and ſo their families or ſervants ſo far off from their ſettled Congregations, as that they cannot poſſibly come every Sabbath (hardly any) to the Miniſterie there; and therefore muſt either preach one to another, or elſe be utterly without. <hi>I. P.</hi> Beſitles (we are informed from thence) the people, of late, grow more violent in clayming that their pretended libertie and priviledge of publike prophecying, urging for it the writings and arguments of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Rob.</hi> the Browniſt, ſometimes alſo contemning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting their own Miniſters and Churches, becauſe they are not ſuffred to injoy it. <hi>M. B.</hi> to <hi>S. A.</hi>
                  </note> unfurniſhed with officers, or in caſe of their abſence or ſickneſſe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 77.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Alſo after their Preaching they take upon them to bleſſe the people at their diſmiſſion, as the Miniſters doe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Likewiſe they have a courſe (before their diſmiſſion) to give leave to any that doubts of any thing that hath been then or formerly delivered in publike by the Miniſter or any other,<note n="a" place="margin">Me thinkes its an abrupt courſe at the firſt daſh openly to implead the Miniſter of errour delivered, before all the people; were it not more civilitie, pietie, charitie, and prudence to talke with him firſt in private: whereby either the doubter may be ſatisfied, or the Miniſter reduced, and both without any moleſtation or ſcandall to the people, or repreach to the Miniſter? Beſides, who muſt be judge in ſuch a caſe, muſt the injudicious multitude? For other judge they will not allow (I meane <hi>in foro externo</hi>) nor any appeale to an higher Court.</note> publikely to propound their doubts, and make their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155017:28"/>objections, and to argue <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> about any matter good for edification. <hi>W. T.</hi> to <hi>P. H. Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 78. <hi>Cot. cat. p.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barr. diſcov. p.</hi> 139. <hi>Johnſ. Inq. p.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Of late, ſome of them grow ſhy of the word Independent, <hi>H. P.</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Reader. Some ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly renounce it, <hi>Apol. Narr. p.</hi> 23. But yet its generally owned by moſt in the name, <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B. p.</hi> 9. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q p.</hi> 46, 47, 64, 65. by all in the thing, as after, <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q p.</hi> 43, 44, 46.</note>
                     <hi>independencie of one Church upon another, and the Combination of ſeverall Churches together, in Claſſes, Synods, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THey grant that Churches may and ought to conſult and adviſe one with another, in any doubtfull matter incident, and ought to hearken to the good advice of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. And therefore they ſometimes allow combinations of divers Churches for conſultation: But not<note n="c" place="margin">They love no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perative Synods or Presbyteries, but they have ſtore of impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches, who may command, yea, compell both members and Miniſters to act, it may be what they like not: why have not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches united as much power over every particular church within the union, as many members united have over every perſon amongſt themſelves.</note> imperative or coercive. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 64, 65, 66.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea, <hi>p.</hi> 251.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But that each particular congregationall Church is the ſupreme judicature, whoſe power is abſolute and imperiall, and therefore may and ought to tranſact all things within themſelves without ſeeking or ſubmitting unto any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative concurrence of any other Churches. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>W. R. Cott. cat.</hi> p. 12, 13. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 44, 62, 64, 65, 66. <hi>J. W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rob. juſtif.</hi> p. 107, 112, 444. <hi>Johnſ.</hi> plea, p. 70, 251. <hi>Barr. diſcov.</hi> p. 261.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore they hold it unlawfull for any ſuch combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, whether in Claſſes, (<hi>i.e.</hi> compound Presbyteries) or Synods provinciall, nationall, or others to take upon them authoritatively to determine or decree any thing in matter of doctrine or practiſe, as intending thereby to oblige any more, or others then their own perſons, no not <hi>in foro exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:155017:29"/>
            <head>The Postſcript,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus at length, Good Reader, thou haſt the ſumme of the Church Courſes of our <hi>New England</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; even the way that ſo many that know it not, or cannot judge of it, doe ſo admire, ſo deſire. And which themſelves doe hold forth to us as the onely way of God, with ſuch ſuperlative com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations in their Letters to us, as if it were a perfect <hi>Idea</hi> of the Conſtitution, Diſcipline, and Government ſet up and exerced in and by the Apoſtolique Churches from point to point; from the beginning (till now of late me thinks they begin to abate) [See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> late Letter to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>B.</hi> printed] inculcating what rare and admirable effects it hath produced amongſt them, impatient that any ſhould oppoſe it, or ſo much as queſtion it; yea, threatning us with continuance of the ſword untill we ſhall imbrace it: See M. <hi>Peters</hi> Preface, <hi>p.</hi> 1. excluding and exploding all other wayes as erroneous, falſe, wicked, and ſavouring at leaſt ſtrongly of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtianiſme. But now that I have thus laid it before thee, I leave it to thy judgement (praying God to guide thee aright therein) whether it deſerve all this or no. As for my ſelfe I look for laſhes from many hands and tongues, but in patience (through the help of Chriſt) I ſhall poſſeſſe my ſoul, being ſupported by the conſcience of mine owne integritie. And yet that I may ſomewhat rebate and take off the edge of as many mens diſpleaſure as I may, I ſhall crave leave of thee to adde a few words more in anſwere to ſome of the principall objections in defence of my ſelfe and this Narration. <hi>Object.</hi> It will be ſaid perhaps by ſome that this Narration is falſe, that they beleeve it not, or that they have heard of others the contrary. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I pray it may be conceived and remembred that I have not undertaken to report things as there they really are, (which I could not doe, unleſſe I had been an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) but to collect their own reports of things ſcattered here and there in their own Papers, and preſent them joyntly together to thy view: ſo that, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their reports be true or falſe is nothing to me; If I can cleare it to a candid and ingenuous Reader that I have not miſ-reported their reports, I will be guiltleſſe both before God and men: For my part I beleeve their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports to be true, as here they are repreſented to thee: Seeing they come not from malignants amongſt them, or enemies to them, nor yet from men of ſmall or no credit, but ſuch as are members at the leaſt of their Churches,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:155017:29"/>and therefore true and reall Saints, which will not, at leaſt, ſhould not lye; yea, many of them officers, and ſome, yea, moſt of them Miniſters of the Word in their Churches, who as they cannot be thought to be ignorant of, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in their courſes, ſo much leſſe can they be reaſonably ſuſpected of falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or partialitie in their relations; At leaſt, ſhall not by me, who both ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently know the fidelitie of the moſt of theſe from whom theſe intelligences come, and alſo have been by ſome of them ſo often chaſtened for making any doubt thereof. But ſuppoſe theſe reports ſhould not be true, or that others of them ſhould report otherwiſe, this may perhaps impeach their credit, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mine; and I ſhall deſire of him whoſoever he be that ſhall call the truth of this Relation in queſtion (for ſubſtance at leaſt) that he himſelfe would put forth a truer. It is a ſmall thing to ſay, They hold not or they doe not this or that, but tell us what they doe hold and practiſe, that we may be miſted no longer, as hitherto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if this report he crue, yet (if you thinke they doe evill) you ſhould rather conceale your brothers faults and errours, Love covers the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Love covers what ſinnes may be covered, but ſome ſinnes cannot be covered, they are ſo publikely committed; and ſome may not, though they could, becauſe the concealment of them may doe hurt, to themſelves or others, the publike, or private wealth: in which caſe it were both againſt Pietie, Charitie, and Prudence to conceale them. In both theſe reſpects, I conceive, their courſes are not to be covered; Firſt, they cannot, at leaſt in great part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing long ſince made publike to the world, and daily are more and more by their own printing, preaching, and private inſtilling them into others. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they may not, if they could; ſeeing by forbearance all this while they have fretted like a Gangrene into the bowels both of citie and countrey; and I feare we have kept their counſell ſo long, that many of them are already paſt cure in their errour, and we almoſt remedileſſe in our rents, tending unto ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> You ſhould rather have confuted them by arguments, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is already done in part by others, and the preſſe is ſtill in travell, readie to bring forth more and new confutations of them. 2. This is none of the worſt wayes of confuting them, as I conceive; To relate them fully is to confute them ſufficiently in the judgement of men judicious and uningaged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> You ſeeme by your paralell places quoted to accuſe them of Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, wherein you highly wrong them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, I doe ſo, and let the Reader judge upon examination and comparing of the places alledged, if it be not ſo: nay, if in ſome things they doe not build up an higher partition wall betweene themſelves and all other churches then ever the Browniſts did, as in their ſtrict examination of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, in urging a Church covenant diſtinct from the covenant of grace, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Beſides, to what hath been ſaid in the Narration, we may adde for further probabilities, and juſt cauſes of our feare in this kind, that 1. They ſometimes cite, and approve of the Browniſts Books in queſtions between us and them,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:155017:30"/>and provoke us to anſwer them: So we are informed from ſome of themſelves <hi>(P. B.)</hi> that they cite <hi>Rob.</hi> book for prophecie, and hold it unanſwerable in that point: And their party here boaſt much of <hi>Robijuſtif,</hi> and bid us anſwer it, if we can: which book is alſo in ſome ſort approved by the Miniſters of <hi>N. E.</hi> in their Apology for Church covenant, <hi>p.</hi> 30. 2. They uſe the ſame arguments, and produce the ſame texts of Scripture to the ſame purpoſes, as whoſoever readeth their writings may obſerve. 3. They condemne their courſes but coldly, with a <hi>quarenus,</hi> only ſo far and ſo far, their rigiditie onely, not ſimply their ſeparation, <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 9. <hi>Poſ. p.</hi> 13. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 30. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 41, 42. They profeſſe it there be any ſeparating opinion amongſt them they hold not themſelves bound to inquire after it, nor to ſeparate from the Browniſts for their ſeparating from us, <hi>I. W.</hi> anſ. to 10. <hi>queſt.</hi> | <hi>M. H.</hi> anſ. to <hi>I. P.</hi> 4. They diſtinguiſh of ſeparations, one they call moderate, the other rigid or bitter, this they condemne, but that they owne. But what they meane by this rigid ſeparation, we well know not, for even the Separatiſts themſelves doe conde nine each others rigour, the latter generally condemne ſome bitterneſſe uſed againſt our Churches by <hi>Barrow,</hi> and <hi>Greenwood:</hi> And of the latter alſo, ſome (as <hi>Robinſon</hi>) were far more moderate then the reſt, yet were all of them complete Separatiſts, and ſo may theſe our brethren be too, notwithſtanding that diſtinction. 5. They aſſociate themſelves in private communion, and in Church communion too with them: So Maſter <hi>H.</hi> to <hi>I. P.</hi> acknowledgeth and juſtifies it alſo. See the Preface to Maſter <hi>G.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Maſter <hi>B.</hi> againſt <hi>Canne.</hi> And we are credibly informed that <hi>H. P.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament in a Browniſts Church here in <hi>London;</hi> yea, ſome aſſure us of profeſt correſpondence and agreement between ſome of our late Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts themſelves; and thoſe of the Separation here, only that they have adviſed them to be moderate in their courſes. 6. The Browniſts themſelves doe claime them as their own, and boaſt of them. See Maſter <hi>G.</hi> defence of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> againſt <hi>Canne</hi> in the <hi>Preſace.</hi> 7. Though in the generall they profeſſe to differ much from them, yet when it comes to reckoning we find it not ſo: which that it may appeare the better, let us he are our brethren them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves expreſſe the differences: <hi>Epiſt. before the anſ. to the</hi> 9. <hi>Poſitions,</hi> p. 53, 60. <hi>They (i.e. the rigid Separatiſts) ſeparate from your Congreg. as no Churches, from the Ordinances dispenſed by you as meere Antichriſtian, and from your ſelver as no viſible Chriſtians:</hi> and ſo in divers other places, Now excepting the laſt, which is proper to the moſt rigid, rigid Browniſts of all as <hi>Barrow,</hi> &amp;c. which the more moderate do utterly diſlike as well as theſe our brethren, <hi>Rob. juſtif p.</hi> All the reſt for ought I yet ſee (putting in the word <hi>unlawfull</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> as a milder terme; and by Ordinances underſtanding Church ordinances, as they needs muſt they cannot refuſe by their Principles and practiſes but to own them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> By no meanes, for they confeſſe your Parochiall Congregations to be true Churches, which the other doe utterly denie. <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, in words they doe, but in effect it is far otherwiſe. 1. In that they lay the ſelfe ſame principles that the moderater ſort of Browniſts doe, touching Church Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, Matter, Forme, Power, Government, Communion, corruptions, &amp;c.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:155017:30"/>which being granted, the naturall product of ſuch premiſes muſt needs be that we have no true Churches, and that our Ordinances are all unlawfull. 2. By carrying themſelves towards us, as if we were no true Churches, or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of true Churches, for they denie our beſt and moſt eminent Chriſtians all Church Communion with them, ſo they doe not to the members of any of the Churches of their own way; they withdraw themſelves from all Church communion with us in the beſt and pureſt of our Aſſemblies, ſo they doe not from the Browniſts: and whereas they hold they may not lawfully admit of the members of other Churches without power given them ſo to doe, by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Recommendations from the ſaid Churches, yet they not only admit, but invite thouſands of the members of our Churches to their communion without, yea, againſt their conſents. 3. Sometimes they approve of us but faintly and coldly, many faults they find with our Churches, little or nothing worthy of commendation in regard of our Church eſtate, or Church ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 38. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 25, 26, 27, 31. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 36. And when they would ſeeme to juſtifie, and pleade for us, yet then they doe it with ſuch uncouth and far fetcht proofes, as we know not whether to accept or refuſe their acknowledgement of the truth of our churches upon ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions be the worſe bargain; as when they ſay we have true Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe knit together in Church covenant, though implicite, becauſe we had true Churches planted here (in the <hi>New England</hi> frame) in the Apoſtles times, and perhaps alſo ſince, &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q p.</hi> 26. <hi>Diſcourſe of Cov. p.</hi> 36, 37. <hi>R. M.</hi> to <hi>E. B.</hi> 4. Some of them come off as roundly as any Browniſts doe, and tell us plainly that in deed we have good Materials, but we want forme, our Churches are Babels, harlots, Maſter <hi>M.</hi> to <hi>I. M.</hi> | <hi>I. R.</hi> to his parents. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>S.</hi> to <hi>I. B.</hi> That we have true Churches, no right Sacraments, nor Miniſters, <hi>I. S.</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>is <hi>B.</hi> | <hi>I. P.</hi> to <hi>W. R.</hi> | <hi>R. W.</hi> to <hi>I. L.</hi> | M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>M.</hi> to <hi>I. M.</hi> | M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>L.</hi> to his parents, &amp;c. And threaten us with deſtruction <hi>eo nomine,</hi> inviting therefore all they can to depart from us, as from Babel, <hi>Ibid.</hi> and doctrinally teaching ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from us, as a dutie, <hi>Anſ.</hi> to 32. <hi>q. p.</hi> 32. And herein ſome of them are ſo cruelly kinde unto us, that they profeſſe to be grieved that we have here any Preaching or Ordinances at all in our way, wiſhing we had none at all, that ſo we might be forced to fall into their Church-wayes for the enjoyment of them. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>M.</hi> to <hi>I. M.</hi> And what is here ſaid of their opinion of the truth of our Churches, the ſame is for ſubſtance to be underſtood of the truth of our Church Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> You may as well call the good old non-conformiſts Browniſts, as theſe men who have followed them (in theſe their opinions and practiſes) as their guides. <hi>Anſw.</hi> In like manner doe the Browniſts father their ſeparation alſo upon the Non-conformiſts; but both forts do it unjuſtly: that the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts doe it unjuſtly, he that will may ſee by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Balls</hi> book againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Canne</hi> upon that very point, and in good part by another book lately printed, called a grave confutation of the errours of the Browniſts made long ſince by ſundry Godly Divines, which in their times ſuffred in the cauſe of inconformitie: For my ſelfe at this time I may not, I will not attempt to give ſatisfaction at large to this objection, onely this I ſay for the preſent that in ſuch things
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:155017:31"/>wherein either the Browniſts, or theſe brethren do mainly differ from other the beſt reformed Churches, they have no conſent or approbation from the Non-conformiſts at all; nay, contrarily by many undeniable evidences from their writings and practiſes it will appeare that they have ever ſtiffely oppoſed and conflicted with all popular and independent government, in behalfe of that we call Presbyteriall. True, indeed ſome of them, eſpecially in their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemicke writings, while they had the Prelacie in their eye, and no conſiderable adverſarie, but that to conteſt withall, did perhaps ſomewhat unwarily (as may befall the beſt, and beſt learned men in ſuch caſes) let fall ſome few things, which thoſe brethren make their advantage of; As that 1.2 particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church ought onely to conſiſt of one Congregation. 2. That each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church hath power to tranſact all its own matters. 3. That this power is ſeated in the body: Many more then theſe I doe not now remember, which are in queſtion between us and theſe brethren. But 1. theſe things they hold not as now cur brethren doe: as if every ſmall company of 7.8. or 9. might make ſuch a complete Church or Congregation to tranſact all their own buſineſſes independently, without aſſiſtance of or being accountable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to claſſicall or higher combinations, nor that this power is ſeated in ſuch a Congregation without their officers, or that they can exerciſe it any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes but by them: But if any of them have gone far, as its more then I know, ſo its more then I will defend: But if all theſe in the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts ſenſe-were granted, it would doe our brethren little good. 2. Beſides ſuppoſe they had the Non-conformiſts their guides in theſe three and three more of their Church courſes in queſtion, yet would not this reach to cover and hide the nakedneſſe of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> We ſee the moſt of the better ſort goe this way now. <hi>Anſw.</hi> I beleeve not the moſt by many; but if it were ſo, that were no good argument to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it. 1. Becauſe of thoſe that doe go that way, a great number are Anabaptiſts, Familiſts and Antinomians, &amp;c. who all willingly chooſe to fall into the ſame channell of popularitie and independencie, perhaps partly out of deſigne, to make a more conſiderable (I ſay not ſormidable) party, that ſo either for favour or feare, they may be the more indulged; partly becauſe it ſuites ſo well with mans proud nature; for every man by his good will would rule, and no man would willingly depend upon or be obnoxious unto another. 2. Moſt good mens affections are ſtrong, when oft their judgements are weake. 3. All men are ever apt to run into extremes, hence it is that whiles they fly prelaticall tyranny, they eaſily fall into popular Anarchy. 4. The noveltie of the courſe. 5. The peoples good opinion of the perſons that way ſiding and drawing. 6. And the advantage the ſaid perſons have had, whereby to ſcrew themſelves further and further into the peoples good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affection, by being ever imployed in the chiefeſt work of the miniſterie in ſome of the chiefeſt of our Churches, although they have been ſo farre from acknowledging themſelves miniſters, as that they doe not ſo much as acknowledge themſelves as members of any of our Churches, but as to us (according to their own rule) altogether without.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> This ſeemes to reflect upon our brethren that come out of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:155017:31"/>but theſe are not ſo rigid as the reſt; what is this Relation to them? <hi>Arſw.</hi> It concernes them I grant not ſo much, nor ſo directly, yet in ſome ſort it doth: 1. Becauſe ſometimes they tell us they are of the ſame way with the <hi>N. E.</hi> brethren. 2. Both their diſputes and practiſes ſo farre as they are knowne doe all look that way. 3. Their lying ſo cloſe lockt up and reſerved in many things makes them (I conceive not without cauſe) the more ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; For truth ſeeks no corners, no cloaks. If therefore now by this occaſion they would pleaſe to put out according to their promiſe, not a mock-Natra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, a meere gull, ſuch as the laſt was, but (as a true ſo) a full, perfect and plaine diſcovery of their opinions in theſe things from point to point, and from end to end, I ſhould heartily rejoyce, as in the much deſired fruit of this my poore labour; That ſo all miſunderſtandings and miſpriſtons being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and we rightly enformed of the juſt latitude of their and our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: we might either more hopefully addreſſe our ſelves to ſatisfie their judgements, or elſe (if that cannot be obtained) the more willingly conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to move (with them) for the favouring of their conſciences, according to the rules of Pietie and prudence, in ſuch things as are capable of tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and indulgence. But leſt (good Reader) I ſhould be tedious to thee, I will ceaſe to purſue theſe things any further at this time. And praying the God of peace and truth to ſend down his Spirit into all our hearts to lead us into both, that we, with all his, may truth it in love, and may all ſerve one God with one heart according to one way, even his own will revealed in his Word. To him I commit thee.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
